<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The cabinet open'd, or, The secret history of the amours of Madam de Maintenon, with the French king translated from the French copy.</title>
            <title>Cassette ouverte. English</title>
            <author>Maintenon, Madame de, 1635-1719.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1690</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 122 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 77 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-04">2011-04 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A31643</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing C190</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R216402</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">12266092</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 12266092</idno>
            <idno type="VID">58078</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A31643)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 58078)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 131:18)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The cabinet open'd, or, The secret history of the amours of Madam de Maintenon, with the French king translated from the French copy.</title>
                  <title>Cassette ouverte. English</title>
                  <author>Maintenon, Madame de, 1635-1719.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[10], 143 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for Richard Baldwin ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1690.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Translation of: Cassette ouverte.</note>
                  <note>First ed. in English. Cf. NUC pre-1956.</note>
                  <note>Advertisement: p. [1].</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Maintenon, --  Madame de, 1635-1719.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-01</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-01</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-03</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-03</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-04</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="publishers_advertisement">
            <pb facs="tcp:58078:1"/>
            <head>ADVERTISEMENT.</head>
            <p>THe Memoires of Monſieur <hi>Deageant:</hi> Containing the moſt ſecret Tranſactions and Affairs of <hi>France,</hi> from the Death of <hi>Henry IV.</hi> till the beginning of the Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtry of the Cardinal <hi>de Richelieu.</hi> To which is added, a Particular Relation of the Arch-Biſhop of <hi>Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brun</hi>'s Voyage into <hi>England,</hi> and of his Negociation for the advance<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of the Roman Catholick Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion here; together with the Duke of <hi>Buckingham</hi>'s Letters to the ſaid Arch-Biſhop about the Progreſs of that Affair: Which happen'd the laſt Years of King <hi>James I.</hi> his Reign. Faithfully Tranſlated out of the <hi>French</hi> Original. Printed for <hi>Richard Baldwin</hi> in the <hi>Old-Baily. 1690.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:58078:1"/>
            <p>THE Cabinet Open'd, OR THE Secret Hiſtory OF THE AMOURS OF Madam <hi>de Maintenon,</hi> With the French KING.</p>
            <p>Tranſlated from the French Copy.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>London,</hi> Printed for <hi>Richard Baldwin,</hi> in the <hi>Old-Baily,</hi> 1690.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="preface">
            <pb facs="tcp:58078:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:58078:2"/>
            <head>THE Author's Preface TO THE READER.</head>
            <p>LOve and Fortune produce effects ſo fantaſtick and ſurprizing, that a man that accuſtoms himſelf to make reflections
<pb facs="tcp:58078:3"/>on all Occurrences, cannot conſider 'em without aſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhment. One ſees not on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly the vileſt and moſt ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject creatures rais'd by this means to the higheſt ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation of Glory and Gran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deur; but one alſo ſees the most agreeable and haugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of all the Sex, thrown down from their greatneſs, by the Caprices of theſe bru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tal paſſions, and the Chi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merique effects of the ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gination,
<pb facs="tcp:58078:3"/>to which ſtupid men offer incenſe as to a Deity. Nature never wrought half the diverſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties in her productions, as Love and Fortune have done in their Vaſſals and Adorers. Madam <hi>de Maintenon,</hi> the per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon whom we ſhall chooſe to be our Heroine, does abundantly confirm the truth of theſe evident aſſertions; one that the
<pb facs="tcp:58078:4"/>following relation may make to be reputed for a happy perſon, if you place the happineſs of this World in proſperity, in which 'tis confeſs'd ſhe abounds.</p>
            <p>As for the reſt, I am to advertiſe the Reader, that altho' ſeveral perſons, having wrote upon the like ſubjects, have deliver'd no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing but pure Romance, nevertheleſs what I have Wrote is an unqueſtiona<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble
<pb facs="tcp:58078:4"/>truth; for the better part of the Memoires, from whence this Little History is drawn, came out of the Cabinet of Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dam <hi>de Maintenon,</hi> and were partly written with her own Hand. Theſe we recovered of a certain Gentlewoman, who lived a conſiderable time with her, and who had not ſerved her this trick, but only to avoid a greater miſchief
<pb facs="tcp:58078:5"/>which was deſigned her, and ſhe avoided by her flight. Therefore, what we received of her, we are now going to expoſe to the publick; and this it is, which has given occaſion to the Title of this Book. I hope the World will re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive ſome ſatisfaction by it, ſince I have given my ſelf the trouble to put to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether theſe Memoires, and digeſt 'em into a method.
<pb facs="tcp:58078:5"/>If you meet with any thing that is ridiculous, you are only to accuſe the Original, and not the Copy.</p>
            <closer>
               <salute>Farewel.</salute>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:58078:6"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:58078:6"/>
            <head>THE SECRET AMOURS OF Madam <hi>de Maintenon,</hi> With the French KING.</head>
            <p>AMongſt all thoſe Effects that Love has produced, one ſees nothing that ſurprizes him more, than when it joyns the Scepter to the Crook, and by its influences
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:58078:7"/>makes thoſe Conditions of Life that ſtand at the greateſt diſtance from one another, ſo united and reconciled, that the two Parties forget not only what they have been, but alſo what they owe to themſelves: Several Examples have acquainted us with the truth of this Aſſertion, but we have not any Inſtance that has demon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrated it with that clearneſs, or is more univerſally known in our Age, than This which we are going to relate.</p>
            <p>Madam <hi>de Maintenon</hi> owes her Nativity to <hi>America:</hi> Her Father who had been formerly one of thoſe righteous Perſons, that we uſe to tranſport for their Civil Behaviour, after he had made Satisfaction for the Slavery, to which he was Condemned, took a little piece of Ground, and planted it with Tobacco. With
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:58078:7"/>the Revenue of this ſmall Terri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tory, he made an hard ſhift to keep Body and Soul together; when Providence, to let him ſee, that he had faln into a Terreſtial Paradiſe, furniſhed him with a comfortable Importance, and ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fered a certain Veſſel that was plentifully laden with all ſorts of Females, to arrive at the Iſland <hi>de la Martinique.</hi> Theſe virtuous Ladies conſidering the Corrupti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the Age, and the Fruitfulneſs of the new World, after having ſacrificed their Bodies for ſome time to the Goddeſs of Pleaſure, and performed all Acts of Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity to thoſe who begg'd it at their hands, departed from their reſpective Habitations in <hi>Low-Poictou,</hi> and out of a Spirit of Submiſſion, to which they were obliged by the Orders of Juſtice, ſurrendred themſelves at <hi>Rochel.</hi>
               <pb n="4" facs="tcp:58078:8"/>Here the report of their Actions gathered a vaſt Company of Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple together, who ran from all parts to behold them with Admi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration. The reſpect they met with, was ſo extremely great, that the Magiſtrates of the place, not thinking any ordinary Houſe worthy to entertain Perſons of their high Character, lodged them in the moſt Magnificent Building of the whole City, as well in regard of its Height, as of its Scituation, and Structure. Their Quarters were aſſigned them in the Tower <hi>de la Lanterne,</hi> where they paſſed ſome time without any manner of Diver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion for want of Needles. After a ſhort ſtay, like true multiply<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Daughters of <hi>Eve,</hi> they em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>barqued for <hi>America,</hi> where they arrived, as we told you before: Preſently after their Landing,
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:58078:8"/>they were joyned to the Tune of <hi>for better for worſe,</hi> according to the laudable Cuſtom of the Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try, which, as we are credibly in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed, was taking one anothers Words without any tedious Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>face or Ceremony; and amongſt the reſt, Madam <hi>de Maintenon</hi>'s Father and Mother were coupled together, and ſo by this means our Illuſtrious <hi>Heroine</hi> came to be begotten. All thoſe Perſons who have been at <hi>America,</hi> are able to inform you, that whether it happens through the peculiar Nature of the Climate, or the Temperature of the Country, their Children don't ſtay ſo long a time before they are able to help themſelves, as here in <hi>Europe;</hi> and Experience has made it evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent, that their Infants do com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monly make a ſhift to walk, when they are but one year Old,
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:58078:9"/>which would paſs for an extraor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinary Miracle, with us on this ſide the Globe. To reaſſume our Diſcourſe, our little <hi>Heroine</hi> was employed at the Age of Three years, to look after ſome Turkies belonging to the Illuſtrious Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dam <hi>de</hi> . . . her Godmother, who out of a Principle of Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity took her from her Pious Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rents, and kept her with her at her own Manſion. In this honou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable important Occupation, ſhe paſſed Three years more, after which time was expired, her above-mentioned Godmother, ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving ſome occaſions to make a Voyage into <hi>Europe,</hi> carried the pretty Damoſel along with her, with a deſign to cultivate and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fine her Perſon as ſhe advanced in Age.</p>
            <p>Their Voyage, as it happened, was ſomewhat of the longeſt,
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:58078:9"/>which they, poor Souls, never ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pected, by reaſon of the ill Wea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther with which they were fre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quently diſtreſſed. Nevertheleſs they arrived happily at <hi>Rochel,</hi> where after they had refreſhed themſelves for ſome time, they took their way towards <hi>Low-Poictou,</hi> and there they tarried a conſiderable ſpace, without any reverſe of Fortune. The firſt Calamity which befel our <hi>Hero<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ine</hi> was the unexpected Death of her Godmother. At that time, ſhe was about Fifteen years Old; the deceaſe of her careful Fellow-Traveller touched her very ſenſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly; and, without queſtion, ſhe wiſhed her ſelf an hundred times in <hi>America</hi> again. We may ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gine, that in this Melancholy Condition, ſhe had remain'd with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out any Comfort; if a Brawny Ruſtick of the Village where ſhe
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:58078:10"/>ſojourn'd, had not prevail'd upon her by Virtue of his Comple<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments to believe, that whatſoever Loſs ſhe had ſuſtained by the Tranſlation of her Godmother, might be fully made up in him. This amorous Villager had Riches enough for a Man of his Quality, he had one Leg ſhorter than the other, and an Eye leſs than other Men, but to make him amends, Nature provided him with a tolerable good Addi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion upon his Back, for he always carried a Mountain about him. After all, I ſay, one could not find in all the Village, a Man that could ſurpaſs him; he had like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe a little ſhare of Underſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, which was but very neceſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, conſidering the buſineſs he went through, and yet a Man may ſay without flattery to his Perſon, that it was not much for
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:58078:10"/>his advantage. A long time be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the Death of our <hi>Heroin</hi>'s Godmother, he had a certain in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clination towards her, that can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not be well expreſſed; for he per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived in himſelf a ſmall <hi>Je ne ſcay quoy,</hi> a beginning of a Paſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, which he durſt not diſcover. Without doubt, the Veneration he bore to Madam <hi>de</hi> . . . the Godmother of our Madam <hi>de Maintenon,</hi> hindred him from making a Formal Declaration of his affection; but as ſoon as ſhe was dead, he ſearched all the means in the World to accoſt her, he never ſung at high Maſs when he was there, nor in any famous Aſſembly of the Village, when he made his appearance amongſt them; If he went to any Fair of note, he laid out his Money very profuſely, on Ribands of all Sorts and Colours, to preſent
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:58078:11"/>them to his fair Miſtreſs, hoping by that Liberality to inſinuate himſelf into her good Graces. But all this while he made but ſmall inſenſible advances in his Affair by his dumb Language, and we may honeſtly conclude, that all theſe Aſſiduities had been to no purpoſe, if he had not found occaſion to accoſt her one day with his Rural Rhetorick, as ſhe was drawing water out of a Well. <hi>Will you let me help you,</hi> ſays he, <hi>Alas,</hi> replys the Damoſel, <hi>You'l mightily oblige me;</hi> ſo he put himſelf in a Poſture to execute the Buſineſs, and through an ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſs of Civility, carried her Buckets for her even to her Cot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tage, where being arrived, and finding himſelf alone with her, <hi>Is it not true,</hi> ſays he, <hi>That you ſuffer a great deal of Sorrow-for the loſs of your Godmother;
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:58078:11"/>She was a very good Woman, and had a mighty Concern for you, and if ſhe had lived any time longer, had not failed to give you ſome lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle Fortune, that might have made you an agreeable Match for ſome ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſt Labourer in the Village: But,</hi> crys he, purſuing his Diſcourſe, <hi>although She has left you nothing at all, yet I have Love enough for you, to give you a Moiety of what I poſſeſs, if you'l be pleas'd to be my Wife; you ſhall always conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nue to command me upon all occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions, and nothing ſhall be wanting for you. Do but allow me,</hi> anſwers ſhe, <hi>a ſmall time to conſider of this matter, and Ple return you my An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer to morrow behind our Cottage.</hi> Our amorous <hi>Eſop</hi> was exceeding ſatisfied with this Anſwer, and after having entertained her a while with his Gallantry upon this Subject, retired and with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drew,
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:58078:12"/>impatiently expecting the following day, to know her final Reſolution, ſo he failed not to ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear upon the place, at the hour of Aſſignation. When he ſaw her a pretty way off, <hi>Alas!</hi> ſays he, <hi>and will you be my Wife then? I don't know,</hi> ſays ſhe, <hi>I find not any great reluctancy in my ſelf, to enter into thoſe Eccleſiaſtical Indentures with you, but to confeſs the Truth, I have no very great Affection for your perſon at preſent, however, I am in good hopes that a little time will bring all theſe Matters about. Ah! My dear</hi> Guiellemette, ſays he, <hi>how paſſionately do I love you, I'le make you ſuch Preſents, and give you ſuch undeniable Teſtimonies of the Sincerity of my heart, that you ſhall be in a manner forced to have a Love for me.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <pb n="13" facs="tcp:58078:12"/>In effect, he went to none of the Neighbouring Markets, but he courteouſly brought her either a Cake-offering, or Buns, or Needles, or Pins, or Penny-knives, and a great quantity of other things of that Nature. She that ſaw with what Zeal and Affection he beſtirr'd himſelf in her Service, began at laſt to have ſome kind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs for him. She conſider'd, ſhe was without Father, and Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, Relations, or Friends, to ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>port her, deſtitute of all manner of Conveniencies, and as it were a Stranger in the Country: On the other hand, ſhe ſaw a ſtrong, luſty, two-handed Labourer, that courted and ador'd her. Theſe prudent reflections had almoſt prevailed with her to make this ill Choice, but it may be alledg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed for her excuſe, that it had not been the firſt Marriage by
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:58078:13"/>ten thouſand, that neceſſity has occaſioned; for when one ſuffers himſelf to tumble down a Preci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pice, 'tis twenty to one, unleſs the Devil's in him, but that he'l lay hold of the next thing he meets to ſave his Bacon. Therefore ſhe teſtified a vaſt deal of kind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, and more indeed than was uſual, for her truſty Swain, and there's no queſtion to be made, but the Marriage had ſucceeded, if a certain Lady that lived in a Neighbouring Caſtle, had not taken Compaſſion of her Youth, and the Embarras, ſhe had una<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voidably thrown her ſelf into, by matching with this Villager: and having obſerved in our <hi>He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>roine,</hi> a Spirit and Wit that was capable of attaining to any thing, ſhe took her home along with her, where ſhe lived at firſt un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the Character of a Servant,
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:58078:13"/>and afterwards under That of a Chamber-maid. There ſhe for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>got her poor Ruſtick to all Intents and Purpoſes, and began to ſhew by little and little the greatneſs of her Soul, <hi>á la mode de la Nobleſſe.</hi> Her diſconſolate Lover was in Deſpair for loſs of her; he was almoſt come up to the Caſtle to ſee her, but he wiſely bethought himſelf, that he could not make his approaches any further, if he deſigned to carry back with him a bundle of Fagots, which he had got upon his Shoulders. This threw him into one of the ſeve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſt Fits of Melancholy in the World, nevertheleſs to relieve him in this Affliction, he had hopes ſome time or other to ſpeak with her, and knowing that ſhe would be obliged ſhortly to pay her Devotions all alone at the Pariſh Church, he was reſolved
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:58078:14"/>to renew his correſpondence with her there. In order to put this in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trigue into execution, he came thither very early in the morning, being afraid, as you may imagine of coming too late, and when ſhe was juſt entred the Church he advanced towards her, that he might have the opportunity to converſe with her; but ſhe that found her heart rais'd above the ordinary pitch, by the fine cloaths ſhe wore, a vanity with which ſhe had never been acquainted before, ſcornfully rejected him, and would not hear him ſpeak one ſyllable.</p>
            <p>He had like to have loſt, for good and all, the reſpect that was due to ſo ſacred a place, and was upon the point of reproaching her, for her baſe ingratitude; but his Reaſon proving too powerful for his Paſſion, he waited pati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ently
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:58078:14"/>till the Service was over; and then, as he followed her, he purſu'd her all along with the bittereſt reproaches imaginable, he refreſh'd her memory a thouſand times over, even with the leaſt inconſiderable triffle he had given her; not forgetting the expences he had been at, upon her ſcore, at the Farthing-Cuſtard-Houſe, and the never to be forgotten preſent of a Needle-Caſe. Sometimes he ſwore at her like any Dragon, at other times he made his ſupplica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions to her in the moſt ſubmiſſive manner, humbly deſiring her Lady-ſhip not to forget the ardent Love he had for her. In fine, he put himſelf into an hundred ſeve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral poſtures, but all this ſignified nothing; for all the while ſhe marched on careleſsly, without regarding his complaints, or ſhew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the leaſt concern for him. This
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:58078:15"/>ſevere uſage made ſo deep an im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſion upon the afflicted Labou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rer, that the very ſame day he fell into a violent Feavor, which in a ſhort time carried him out of the World. She could not for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bear the having <hi>un peu de chagrin,</hi> a little interval of ſorrow, upon ſo doleful an occaſion, and the Lord knows it was but very lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle, for two hours put it out of her head, and made her forget the memory of him for ever. She continued a good time in this mid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dle ſtation of Life, and without do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing her any affront, we may ſafely conclude, ſhe had paſſed her whole Life in this humble Figure, if the Marquis <hi>de Chevreuſe</hi> had not found ſome charms in her. The firſt time he ſaw her was in this Ladies family, and having infor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med himſelf of her extraction, he employ'd all his thoughts to make
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:58078:15"/>a conqueſt of her. To bring this about, he attacqu'd her with all the ways and arguments, that he believed would be moſt agreeable to his deſign, and cou'd ſooneſt help to vanquiſh her, but to no purpoſe: She lived with a reſerv'd Virtuous Perſon that had an Eye continually over her; and beſides, had ſufficiently inſtructed her in the principles of Honour, if ſhe wou'd be content to practiſe 'em. Monſieur <hi>de Chevreuſe</hi> who had ſeen the Court, and conſequently knew that ſome feeble denials at firſt were things of courſe, was not overmuch mortify'd or a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtoniſh'd at her refuſal; he daily continued in his purſuit, and did not at all deſpair to accompliſh his ends, and carry off the Game. One day when her Lady was wholly taken up in receiving a Viſit, and ſhe her ſelf, contrary
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:58078:16"/>to her uſual cuſtom, was a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lone in her Chamber, he accoſted her with great civilities. <hi>Ah! Dear Madam,</hi> ſays he to her, <hi>and have you then ſworn to be always cruel to me, and will you not reci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>procally correſpond with the moſt violent and faithful paſſion in the World? I love you, Madam, and I have acquainted you with my flame ſeveral limes, and my Eyes have declar'd it to you, every mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment when I had the happineſs of ſeeing you; yet you, cruel fair one, will not ſuffer it to meet with the leaſt encouragement, but ſeem fully reſolved to make me endure a thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand Martyrdomes, by the contempt with which you entertain my love, and the indifference with which you receive my proteſtations. Monſieur,</hi> anſwers ſhe, very coldly to him, <hi>I have neither any rigour or ſoft<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs in me, in regard to your ſelf;
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:58078:16"/>I know my own inclinations pretty well, and it ſuffices me to have a reſpect for you, which is due to per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons of your Rank and Quality, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out troubling my ſelf with any other matters.</hi> Having ended her diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe, ſhe went haſtily out of her Chamber, and diſpoſed of her ſelf amongſt her companions, the poor Marquis not being able to oblige her to tarry one moment longer with him, for all his im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portunity and ſolicitation. Ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vertheleſs he did not ſuffer any favourable occaſion to paſs by, without diſcourſing to her about his love, and he imagined, that he obſerved ſome proſperous ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vance in his affairs; when he was obliged to go and take poſſeſſion of an Eſtate a great way off, which a certain pious Aunt of his had left him at her deceaſe. Being juſt about to depart out of this
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:58078:17"/>Province, he deſired to take his leave of her, but he was not able to find her alone, becauſe ſhe was always buſied before her Lady, who found her ſelf ſomewhat in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diſpoſed. Therefore he reſolved to write to her, which he im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mediately did, as ſoon as he arri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved to the place, where he was obliged to be; and that his Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtreſs might receive it with ſecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity, he diſpatched one of his Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vants to viſit, as from him, the Lady with whom ſhe lived; with order likewiſe to ſlip the Letter into her hands when he ſaw an opportunity, which he accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dingly did. When ſhe had received it, ſhe cou'd not tell, whether it was beſt to deliver it to her Miſtreſs, or read it by her ſelf. Her mind continued ſome time in this ſuſpence, at laſt her curioſity prevailed, ſo ſhe opened it, and read as follows.</p>
            <floatingText type="letter" xml:lang="eng">
               <body>
                  <pb n="23" facs="tcp:58078:17"/>
                  <opener>
                     <salute>Madam,</salute>
                  </opener>
                  <p>AFter having oftentimes aſſur'd you in converſation, that I love you more than my ſelf, I take the liberty to write to you; that I may give you fuller evidences of my ſincerity, and at the ſame time to make this proteſtation before you, that notwithſtanding all your indifference, I ſhall ever perſevere to adore you. I am ſenſibly afflicted that I had not the honour to take my leave of you before my departure; I have ſought every occaſion with the utmoſt dili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gence, but you, my cruel fair one, think, that I am not ſufficiently pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhed for my tranſgreſſions either by your rigour, or my owndeſpair. You have hitherto induſtriouſly avoided my company, becauſe you very well fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaw that one moment of your charm<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing converſation wou'd ſweeten and lenify all that <hi>chagrin</hi> which your
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:58078:18"/>abſence had created. Let me per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuade you, Madam, to quit all thoſe cruelties that are ſo diſagreeable and contrary to the faireſt Sex, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider the violence of my paſſion, and by an act of generoſity, which is ſo peculiar to your nature, return one heart for another. Mine is altoge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther yours, it will ſuffer no other image to be impreſt upon it, but that of your charming perſon, nor will it be ever ſeparated from you. Give me therefore ſome ſmall room in yours; 'tis the only thing in the World which I beg of you, and for the attaining of it, I would willingly abandon my fortune, and my dignity. Let me then conjure you, Madam, to com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply with my paſſion, and make your ſelf abſolute Miſtreſs, not only of my Heart, but alſo of every thing that I poſſeſs. The Bearer hereof will bring me your anſwer; I beſeech you, that you'l no more deny me this fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour,
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:58078:18"/>than any thing elſe that I have requeſted of you; without which you'l reduce to the extremity of de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpair the perſon, that preſerves his life upon no other ſcore than to love, nor his Fortunes, than to ſerve you.</p>
                  <closer>
                     <signed>De Chevreuſe.</signed>
                  </closer>
               </body>
            </floatingText>
            <p>She continued for ſome ſpace altogether aſtoniſhed at reading this Letter, and cou'd not tell whether ſhe had beſt return any anſwer or no; at laſt ſhe reſol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved with her ſelf not to write to him, and to avoid-meeting with the Meſſenger ſhe paſs'd the time amongſt her Female companions till he was gone. After this, ſhe took a walk all alone by her ſelf to a pretty Grove of Trees that was joyning to the Houſe; where ſhe had not been long, but ſhe was poſſeſſed with an itching deſire
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:58078:19"/>to review the Letter; ſhe endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour'd with ſome little violence to her ſelf to maſter this inclina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, but the curioſity, which is ſo natural to her Sex, at laſt carried it. Immediately ſhe imagined, that it would prove a very a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greeable diverſion, and that an hundred Letters of that nature cou'd not fail to get the aſcendent over her heart. Having there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore pleaſed her ſelf with the per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uſal of it, ſhe began to diſcover ſome graces in the Style, which attracted her Eyes as it were by force. In fine, ſhe read it again with abundance of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap>, and after ſhe had mad<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> few re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flections, found it <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>ertain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing. <hi>How!</hi> (ſays ſhe,) <hi>a Marquit fal'n in love with me, and not only ſo, but paſſionately in love, that of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fers me his Heart, and his fortunes, and ſhall I refuſe him? No, I
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:58078:19"/>begin to ſee my fault, I will love him, he'l make me a great Lady, and inſtead of being a Servant to others, as I am at preſent, I ſhall then have others to wait upon me; I ſhall by this means raiſe and ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vance the obſcurity of my Birth. But then,</hi> ſays ſhe, reprehending her ſelf, <hi>You know who you are, and if he love thee, 'tis only to raviſh from thee the deareſt thing thou haſt <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>n the World. When that is gone, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e'l regard thee no more; then <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>hou'lt be abandon'd, and without ſupport: No, love him not, but reſerve thy reputation and honour.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Thus divided between two dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferent paſſions, ſhe let her Let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter drop without perceiving it. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>he purſu'd her walk and medi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>tions, when an old venerable <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ervant-Maid of the houſe, with <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>hom ſhe was intimately ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>uainted, came thither: She
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:58078:20"/>walked ſo ſoftly, that <hi>Guillemette</hi> was not aware of her till ſhe came up to the place, and had taken up the Letter, which ſhe did very carefully, not at all queſtioning, but that it contain'd ſome impor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tant piece of ſecrecy. She ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>coſted her then, and endeavour'd to drive her out of her penſive<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs. I have never found you, ſays ſhe to her, in ſuch a ſullen reſerved humour before, it muſt certainly be ſome extraordinary matter that has occaſion'd it; Come, don't conceal any of your affairs from me, and if I am able to bring you any conſolation, you may reſt ſatisfy'd, that I ſhall leave nothing unattempted. She ſpoke abundance of ſuch things to her, without being able to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tort any poſitive anſwer; but ſeeing that, ſhe did not any more importune her upon this occaſion,
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:58078:20"/>not at all queſtioning but ſhe ſhould diſcover ſomething or other in the Letter. In ſhort, they were no ſooner arrived to their reſpective apartments, but the old Woman ſhutting the door upon her ſelf, began to read it; and there was fully ſatisfy'd with the true rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon of the change which ſhe ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerved in <hi>Guillemette.</hi> She was extremely concern'd to know, what advances the Marquis had made in her affections, and what effect this Letter had produced. She judged very well, that <hi>Guille<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mette</hi> wou'd not make her any diſcoveries of this Secret, ſo ſhe reſolved to attend, and wait till the return of the Marquis, hoping to get an account of the whole in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trigue out of him; and as ſhe knew by experience, that lovers are generally free and liberal, ſo ſhe promis'd her ſelf no inconſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derable
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:58078:21"/>advantage, if ſhe cou'd but be ſerviceable to him in this Amorous commerce.</p>
            <p>All this while, the penſive <hi>Guillemette</hi> had her mind ſeized with a thouſand ſeveral thoughts, and agitations: She had a deſire once more to read the Letter that gave her all theſe inquietudes, and for that purpoſe, ſhe ſearched her Pockets. Nothing certainly is able to deſcribe her aſtoniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment and confuſion, when ſhe cou'd not find it there: She im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mediately ran to the place where ſhe read it the Second time, but did not meet with it; then ſhe did not at all queſtion but that ſhe was entirely ruin'd in the good opinion of her Lady; a thouſand mortifying reflections diſturbed her Soul, and ſhe found a viſible alteration in her ſelf within a few days. Her Miſtreſs
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:58078:21"/>that loved her very well, deſired to be made acquainted with the reaſon; but ſhe pretended an or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinary indiſpoſition of body, and confeſs'd not one Syllable of the true occaſion. There was no body in the whole Family that knew the cauſe, but only our old <hi>Agnes,</hi> who, being willing to apply a re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>medy to this malady, came im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mediately to her Chamber, and thus began. Ah, my dear <hi>Guille<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mette,</hi> lays ſhe to her, you wou'd not tell me t'other day in the Grove, what it was that poſſeſs'd you with this melancholy, and I believe I had never known the reaſon, if my good Stars had not thrown me upon your Letter, which has diſcover'd the whole buſineſs. 'Tis nothing but the loſs of That, continues ſhe, which has cauſed all your pain; but it has been lodged in very good
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:58078:22"/>hands, behold here I return it you, no body has read it but my ſelf. I have always had a kindneſs for you, and ſhall ever preſerve it; but then to correſpond with my friendſhip, you muſt make me your confident, and for the future conceal none of your Intrigues from me. <hi>Guillemette</hi> took the Letter with a great deal of joy, which did not a little contribute towards her recovery, ſince her indiſpoſition chiefly proceeded from an apprehenſion ſhe had, that her Lady had read the Let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter. In fine, ſhe gave <hi>Agnes</hi> abun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dance of thanks, and repoſed an entire confidence in her Fidelity. The Old Woman contradicted her in nothing, on the contrary ſhe agreed with her exactly in all her Sentiments, in order to make ſome advantages hereafter by this complyance, which was the only
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:58078:22"/>thing that ſhe propos'd to her ſelf by it.</p>
            <p>In the mean time, the Marquis <hi>de Chevreuſe</hi> was in deſpair, for having received no anſwer to his better, he reſolved to write to her the Second time, and if that fail'd to crown his expectation, to make no more efforts of that na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, but go himſelf in Perſon, and endeavour a conqueſt: There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore he took Pen in Hand, and Compoſed a Sonnet, which he cloſed up in the following Billet.</p>
            <floatingText type="letter" xml:lang="eng">
               <body>
                  <p>'TIs I find decreed, Madam, and you have reſolved my death; If that is your deſign, you'l have your ſatisfaction upon me in a few days, for ſince I have been abſent from you, I have not been able to procure one moments releaſe from my torments. However, if you'l be pleaſed to alleviate my pains
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:58078:23"/>with one Word from your adorable hand, I ſhall have the conſolation to be remembred by you. Do it then, I beſeech you, and if you diſdain to anſwer my proſe, at leaſt, anſwer the Verſes, which are ſent you by the moſt Paſſionate and ſincere of Lovers,</p>
                  <closer>
                     <signed>De Chevreuſe.</signed>
                  </closer>
                  <postscript>
                     <q>
                        <floatingText xml:lang="eng">
                           <body>
                              <div type="sonnet">
                                 <head>SONNET To my Adorable <hi>Guillemette.</hi>
                                 </head>
                                 <lg n="1">
                                    <head>I.</head>
                                    <l>FAir Goddeſs, whoſe victorious Charms</l>
                                    <l>Have made a Conqueſt o're my heart,</l>
                                    <l>When will you fill my long-expecting arms,</l>
                                    <l>And bid my cruel fears depart.</l>
                                 </lg>
                                 <lg n="2">
                                    <head>II.</head>
                                    <l>Since envious fate your abſence has procur'd,</l>
                                    <l>No peaceful reſt has crown'd the Night.</l>
                                    <l>The day has ſeen no kind delight,</l>
                                    <l>Ten thouſand Martyrdoms I have endur'd.</l>
                                 </lg>
                                 <lg n="3">
                                    <pb n="35" facs="tcp:58078:23"/>
                                    <head>III.</head>
                                    <l>Come, make a Victim of your pride,</l>
                                    <l>Gave my deſpair, and eaſe my pain,</l>
                                    <l>
                                       <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                                          <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                                       </gap> unbecoming Cruelty aſide,</l>
                                    <l>And to mild pity ſacrifice diſdain.</l>
                                 </lg>
                                 <lg n="4">
                                    <head>IV.</head>
                                    <l>Or of my fate you have decread,</l>
                                    <l>And poor unhappy. I muſt bleed,</l>
                                    <l>In a pathetic tone pronounce my death.</l>
                                    <l>And I with freedom will reſign my breath.</l>
                                 </lg>
                              </div>
                           </body>
                        </floatingText>
                     </q>
                  </postscript>
               </body>
            </floatingText>
            <p>This he ſent by another Valet, hoping that he'd acquit himſelf better in his commiſſion than the laſt, who in a few days arrived at the Caſtle; and after he had viſited the Lady in his Maſter's name, as he was ordered, be waited for an opportunity to find <hi>Guillemette</hi> alone. At laſt, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e had the good fortune to meet with her in the Parterres, and
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:58078:24"/>having ſaluted her with the ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pearance of a moſt profound re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect; he told her, that he had orders to deliver a Pacquet into her own hands, and attend her anſwer. She knew the Livery full well, ſo it coſt her a moment or two's conſideration to conclude whether ſhe ſhould receive the Letter or no. But the Bearer was ſo very adroit in his perſuaſions, and acquitted himſelf ſo hand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſomely, that he oblig'd her to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive it. However all the an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer he was able to get out of her, was only this, that he was not to expect any; he was weary of making a long ſtay, ſince it was not likely to turn to account, therefore he withdrew, and went back to his Maſter; who was no ſooner informed of the ſucceſs of his Second Letter, but he ſent or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders with all the haſte imaginable to diſpatch his Affairs, and prepared
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:58078:24"/>to be going very early next Mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning, as indeed he did, and ſoon arrived at the Ladies houſe.</p>
            <p>Immediately he waited upon her, to pay his Devoirs, but ſtaid not any long time in the Room, out of an impatience he had to talk with his dearly beloved <hi>Guillemette,</hi> who took as much Fains to avoid him, as he did to find her out. She came off well enough for that time, for ſhe took care to be conſtantly in her Ladies Company. The Marquis began to deſpair of the Succeſs of his undertaking, nevertheleſs to conceal his impatience as much, as was poſſible for him, he viſited all the Ladies Maids, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt the reſt as he was paſſing by the Chamber of the reverend Old <hi>Agnes,</hi> he made her ſome Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plements, and as they had known one another for a long time, ſhe
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:58078:25"/>de<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>ed him to come in, and ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving made him to ſit, thus began her Diſcourſe, <hi>I know, Sir, ſome Melancholy Conſideration or other, has of late oppreſſed your Spirits; I don't ſee you in that pleaſant Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry Humour, you were always accu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtomed to carry about you; on the contrary you do nothing in the World but think, and ſigh, and caſt your eyes everlaſtingly upon the Ground. For Heavens ſake, whence proceeds this ſudden Alteration? Come, Sir, deal fairly, and lay aſide your Diſguiſe,</hi> Guillemette <hi>has oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſioned all this Chagrin, don't con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceal any thing from me, and be per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwaded, that I have Compaſſion enough for your Condition, and Friendſhip enough for you, to un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dertake anything in the World that may prove Serviceable to your De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſigns, only tell me what Progreſs you have made in her Affections,
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:58078:25"/>and how your circumſtances ſtand. Since I muſt acquaint you with eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rything, my dear</hi> Agnes, anſwers he, <hi>You are to know, that hitherto ſhe has ſcorned and diſdained me, and ſhuns my Company with as much concern, as if I carried the Peſtilence about me. Endeavour to ſet me right in her good Opinion, and beſides a ſuitable recompence which I ſhall give thee hereafter, behold here are ten</hi> Lew is d'ors, <hi>which I deſire thee to accept.</hi> She made ſome Ceremony at firſt of taking the damn'd Yellow pieces, but in fine ſhe ſuffered him to overcome her Modeſty, and promiſed to ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nage her ſelf upon this occaſion, that he ſhould have no Reaſon to diſcommend her Conduct.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Guillemette</hi> in the mean time, who knew nothing of this Conſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racy againſt her, had no ſooner read the Letter, but out ſhe goes
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:58078:26"/>to find her vertuous Confident <hi>Agnes,</hi> according to her Promiſe, which, as you were informed before, obliged her to conceal no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing from the venerable Old Gentlewoman; ſhe found her as ſhe came from conducting the Marquis to his Lodgings, and im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mediately ſhewed her the Letter, and demanded her Opinion of it. Upon my word, dear Child of mine, replyed the charitable Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tron, I could almoſt find in my heart to quarrel with my Stars, and ſo forth, for not being young, and in a condition to oblige. A Lover ſo ſincere as yours is, ſhould never be able to diſengage him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf from my Chains, and heaven knows, how advantagiouſly I'de manage ſo favourable an oppor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tunity. I give thee, my dear, the ſame Advice which I would follow my ſelf, were I in thy Cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumſtances,
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:58078:26"/>make your Profit of this Affair, and don't neglect it, 'twill turn to a fine Account, I warrant you. Not to over whelm you with an hundred and fifty Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verbes, ſtrike the Iron, I ſay, while it is hot; for that Perſon, that has had the Grace to take the firſt occaſion by the Forelock, will be able to command the other for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tunate Moments, as they happen. In a word, ſhe alledged ſo many convincing Reaſons for what ſhe ſaid, and ſo well employed her little Talent of Rhetorick, that <hi>Guillemette</hi> promiſed her for the time to come to comply with the Marquiſſes Inclinations. Our Old Matron was never better pleas'd in all her Life than now, ſhe immedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ately ſentthe Marquis word in how hopeful a way things were like to go with him, which he was no ſooner informed of; but he
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:58078:27"/>prepared himſelf to give a Viſit to the Lady. After that piece of Formality was over, he walked out to breathe a little freſh Air in the Garden, where it was his Fortune to meet with the Good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>natur'd <hi>Agnes,</hi> who gave him an ample Account of what had paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed, and told him withal, that he might, if he pleaſed, ſee his Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtreſs <hi>Guillemette,</hi> becauſe ſhe was at that very time all alone in her Chamber. He ran thither with all the haſte imaginable, and found her very buſie about her Linen. <hi>At laſt, Madam,</hi> ſays he, <hi>I may count my ſelf the happieſt Man in the <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niverſe, ſince I have one favourable moment to acquaint you with the true Sentiments of my Heart; they are pure, and ſincere. Madam, I love you, I adore you, comply with my Paſſion. How!</hi> continued he, <hi>will you then return
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:58078:27"/>me no Anſwer, will you reduce me to the extremity of Deſpair?</hi> To all this ſhe made no Anſwer but by her ſighs, which gave the Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quis to underſtand, that the Pains of the venerable <hi>Agnes</hi> were not beſtowed in vain, but had operated wonderfully. Never<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>theleſs he could not content him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf with this dumb Language, but conjur'd her by all manner of Reaſons to quit this Silence, he beſeeched her to make ſome E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clairciſſement of her Love, and in fine prevailed ſo far, that he drew this Confeſſion from her Mouth, that ſhe had no Averſion to him. He would needs be aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſured of the Truth of it by a Kiſs, but ſhe was not willing to grant him ſuch a Favour ſo ſoon; in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſing him, ſhe did not however take away all hopes from him to obtain it for the time to come,
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:58078:28"/>but he that was the moſt paſſio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nate Lover breathing, ſeeing he could not have ſo ſmall a refreſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment to his Flame, began to faint away, and had unqueſtionably done ſo, if he had not ſuſtained himſelf by an Elbow-Chair that ſtood near him. As ſoon as he was recovered out of the Fit, look<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing upon her with languiſhing Eyes, he thus Addreſſed him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf to her in the following Sonnet.</p>
            <q>
               <floatingText xml:lang="eng">
                  <body>
                     <div type="sonnet">
                        <head>SONNET.</head>
                        <lg n="1">
                           <head>I.</head>
                           <l>WEll now, imperious Fair, I find,</l>
                           <l>You have your Lovers Death deſign'd:</l>
                           <l>Since you that could have eas'd my wretched ſtate,</l>
                           <l>Have added to my Cares, and urg'd my coming fate.</l>
                        </lg>
                        <lg n="2">
                           <pb n="45" facs="tcp:58078:28"/>
                           <head>II.</head>
                           <l>Go, <hi>take a Kiſs,</hi> Love whiſpers in my Ear,</l>
                           <l>But Love, alas! gives place to Fear;</l>
                           <l>Awful reſpect diſarms my hands.</l>
                           <l>And to my growing Paſſion gives Commands.</l>
                        </lg>
                        <lg n="3">
                           <head>III.</head>
                           <l>Ah! muſt your wounded Lover dye,</l>
                           <l>And ſee his Balm, and ſee his cure ſo nigh.</l>
                           <l>Or ſhall he boldly ſeize a Kiſs,</l>
                           <l>A prelude to a greater Bliſs.</l>
                        </lg>
                        <lg n="4">
                           <head>IV.</head>
                           <l>No, He'l a thouſand Deaths endure,</l>
                           <l>And all reverſes of his fate attend,</l>
                           <l>E're He'l by Sacrilege attempt his cure,</l>
                           <l>And his dear <hi>Guillemette</hi> offend.</l>
                        </lg>
                     </div>
                  </body>
               </floatingText>
            </q>
            <p>This Agitation, and reſpectful Behaviour of the Marquis failed not to make a large breach in the heart of the poor <hi>Guillemette,</hi> yet ſhe had the care enough to conceal it from her Conqueror, and after all his reiterated impor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tunities
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:58078:29"/>made no other Declarati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of her Affections, than what ſhe had done before; Namely, that he was not diſpleaſing or diſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greeable to her.</p>
            <p>Our Marquis immediately gave the diſcreet <hi>Agnes,</hi> a full Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count of the iſſue of his Nego<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiation, and viſited <hi>Guillemette</hi> with the greateſt Aſſiduity as was poſſible, he prevailed ſo far upon her at laſt, that ſhe confeſſed ſhe loved him; he was not ſatis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied with this Confeſſion, but conjur'd her by all the tendereſt things in the World, to anſwer his Love. <hi>Agnes</hi> on the other hand perſwaded her not to ſhew her ſelf too Complaiſant on the ſudden to the Marquis, but to have a regard to the making of her Fortune: In a word, they were ſo well pleaſed one with the other that ſhe promiſed him a rende<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vouz
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:58078:29"/>the next Night at her Chamber, where they might diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe of theſe Affairs, with grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter Liberty and Freedom. But their cruel Deſtinies ſo ordered the Matter, that a certain Lady of Quality in the Neighbour-hood, having loſt two of her Maids by an unlucky Diſtemper, and being informed, that in the Houſe where <hi>Guillemette</hi> lived, they had more than they had occaſion for, ſhe diſpatched a Meſſenger to her Lady, to entreat her, that ſhe would be pleaſed to ſend her one or two. This Lady, who had ſome Suſpicion of the Intrigue that was a driving on betwixt the Marquis and <hi>Guillemette,</hi> was extremely glad, that ſhe had an opportunity to break off the Cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſpondence; and ſo much the more was ſhe ſatisfied, becauſe ſhe knew the Marquis durſt not
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:58078:30"/>appear there, by reaſon of an in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veterate hatred between him and that Family. Therefore ſhe or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dered our unfortunate Lover, and another of her Maids to prepare themſelves to depart the next Morning, and commanded <hi>Guille<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mette</hi> to come that Night, and lye in her Chamber, becauſe ſhe had ſome important Advice to give her for the future manage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of her Life. Never did any mortal blow occaſion, a greater Aſtoniſhment; theſe words ſtruck her like a Thunder-bolt, or like <hi>Meduſa</hi>'s head, for ſhe imagined her ſelf to be changed into ſtone. Her Lady, perceiving the diſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der ſhe was in, was very inquiſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive to know the Reaſon, but ſhe, who had a very good faculty that way, found it it no difficult mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter to invent a ſham Excuſe; the preſent Conjuncture afforded her
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:58078:30"/>a plauſible Pretence, and to give the better Colour to her Hypo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>criſie, ſhe ſhed a few Tears, and thus began her Diſcourſe. <hi>With<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out queſtion, Madam, you are ſuffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciently acquainted with the cauſe of my Grief, but ſince you are pleaſed to learn it from my own Mouth; I dare not aſſume the Confidence to contradict you. I believe, Madam, it will not appear ſtrange in the leaſt to you, that after having re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived ſuch abundance of Favours and Kindneſſes from your liberal hands, I find a ſenſible regret to part with you, eſpecially having de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>termined to paſs the remaining part of my Life in your Service, and by my diligence to make you ſome to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lerable amends for all your Bounty. This only Sorrow, to ſee my ſelf ſo miſerably diſappointed in my Expectations, bas ſofar poſſeſſed me, that I can think of nothing elſe;
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:58078:31"/>and altho' your Injunctions have ever paſſed with me for ſo many Laws, yet I ſhall obey this particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar Command, with the greateſt reluctance in the World; if my Prayers and Supplications could prevail with you to revoke this cruel Order. I have parted with you for your own good,</hi> replys her Lady very bluntly, <hi>but it will not con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinue always; as I find you behave your ſelf, ſo I ſhall Act accordingly; go in the mean time, and prepare to obey me.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>She departed, and run imme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diately to inform <hi>Agnes</hi> of this fatal Command, and enjoyn'd her to tell the Marquis, ſhe would ever preſerve the ſame Affection and Tenderneſs for him; only ſhe de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſired him to attempt nothing up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the Road, for that, ſays ſhe, will raiſe a great Clamour and Noiſe, and diſcover the whole
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:58078:31"/>Affair, which I would have kept as ſecret, as is poſſible. <hi>Agnes</hi> was mightily concerned at this <hi>Contre-coup,</hi> this mortifying diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>appointment, for ſhe grounded no ſmall Expectations upon the Sacrificing of this Virginity. Ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vertheleſs ſhe promiſed to per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>form whatever ſhe had requeſted of her, and preſently poſted a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way to acquaint the Marquis with the News, who by this time had taſted a thouſand Fan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taſtick Pleaſures in his Imagina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion: He fell into the greateſt Conſternation in the World, but had no other Remedy to apply to his Sores, except Patience; and endeavoured to comfort himſelf, as well as he could. As the Night approached, he judged it not <hi>à Propos</hi> to depart, but ſtay till next Morning, that he might give no Umbrage or Suſpicion in
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:58078:32"/>the Caſe, and alſo, that he might find ſome opportunity or other, to ſpeak with his Miſtreſs before his Departure.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Guillemette</hi> having put all her things in her Trunk, received Orders to appear forthwith at her Ladies Chamber. This vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuous Perſon, who had paſſed above Threeſcore years in the World; had gathered a great deal of Experience, and conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dering that a good Tree is eaſily ſpoiled, if it is not cultivated when 'tis young, was deſirous to furniſh her with ſome uſeful So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lid Inſtructions, before ſhe went away, and to that end ſhe thus be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gan the Diſcourſe.</p>
            <q>Since it has pleaſed Heaven to take away my dear Husband and Children from me, I have been effe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctually dead to all theſe imperti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nent
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:58078:32"/>gilded Vanities; of Life, and only paid my regard to thoſe Duties, that cannot but render thoſe Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons eternally happy that follow them. Now becauſe you are going to be ſeparated from me for at me, I have ſome Reaſon to be fearful of your Conduct, when I conſider what Age you are of. One runs a great deal of Hazard and Danger at your years, but withal one ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quires a vaſt Reputation and Glory in ſurmounting them: Therefore I think it not amiſs, to give you part of that Experience which I have, and to lend you ſome Inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions for your future Deport<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment: And I am able to aſſure you, that you cannot prove other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe than Happy, if you'l permit your ſelf to be influenced and dire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted by them.</q>
            <p>
               <pb n="54" facs="tcp:58078:33"/>In the firſt Place be devout with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out Affectation, and have a Care you don't fall into Hypocriſie, for by that one does immediately Af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>front and Aſſault the Divinity.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Don't ſet your Heart upon the Pleaſures of the Fleſh, for he that prefers the Pleaſures of the Body, before the Health of his Soul is Guilty of the ſame ſottiſh Stupidity, with him that let's his Friend drown, and runs to ſecure his Cloaths.</p>
            <p n="3">3. Don't propoſe to your ſelf any great Pleaſure in worldly Vanity, rather abhor it, and let your Garb be Modeſt and Civil; ever while you live take more care to adorn your Soul than your Body, without doing which you offer incenſe to an Idol, and aban<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don the Deity.</p>
            <p n="4">
               <pb n="55" facs="tcp:58078:33"/>4. Don't begin any thing, without having conſider'd ſeri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſly of it before, and let your judgment be mature and well fix<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed: for he that undertakes any buſineſs of moment, without this neceſſary proviſion, ought not to be ſurprized, if it never ſucceeds.</p>
            <p n="5">5. Never attempt any thing which is above your ſtrength, for all efforts of this nature uſe to produce effects that are infi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitely below the expectation one conceived of 'em.</p>
            <p n="6">6. Don't look with Envy at the good of your Neighbour, for by that means you render your ſelf unworthy to poſſeſs your own.</p>
            <p n="7">7. Carefully avoid that which they call Love here in the World. Above all, never give any atten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion to the diſcourſes of Flatterers. This ſort of People deify you in
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:58078:34"/>their warm harangues, tho' at the ſame time they endeavour to make you the moſt miſerable of all Creatures. Therefore in imita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the Adder, ſhut your Ears to the Cllarms of theſe Enchan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters, and be ſtrongly perſuaded, that there is nothing ſo prejudi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cial to your reputation, as the vanity of hearing your ſelf flat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter'd. Of all the paſſions, that are capable of miſleading, and corrupting the judgment, Love is the ſtrongeſt and moſt imper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceptible: for he kindles his Fire only with a deſign to make us blind and giddy; to make you entertain a horror of him, he's Painted blind, not only to repre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent his <hi>Effronterie</hi> and immo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſty, but alſo to teach us, that commonly he reduces thoſe Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons to Nakedneſs and Poverty, that follow him.</p>
            <p n="8">
               <pb n="57" facs="tcp:58078:34"/>8. If you ſubmit your judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment to your pleaſures, you'l burn your ſelf at laſt with the Torch, that was given you to light and conduct you.</p>
            <p n="9">9. Avoid Gaming as much as is poſſible, for he that loves play to exceſs, takes a great deal of pains to die poor.</p>
            <p n="10">10. Conſider one moment at leaſt, of what you are going to ſpeak, and take two more to think of what you are going to promiſe; fearing leſt you may come to feel a great deal of ſorrow, for that which you promiſed with preci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pitation.</p>
            <p n="11">11. Obey with all alacrity and reverence, the perſon whom you Serve, and employ your utmoſt endeavours to ſet your ſelf in her good opinion. Never ſtay for a Command to do that, which you ſee is neceſſary to be done, and
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:58078:35"/>conſider that the principal cauſe of the liberality of Maſters to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards their Servants, proceeds from their having acquitted them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves well in their reſpective du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties; for to apply an old but a Proverb upon this occaſion. <hi>A good Valet makes a good Maſter.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="12">12. Be content with your own condition, for he that is not con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent with an honeſt condition, gives himſelf the trouble often<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times to render that leſs, which he endeavour'd to encreaſe.</p>
            <p n="13">13. Don't be urgent or preſſing to know the Secrets of another; be likewiſe very reſerv'd, in com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>municating your own. You are no longer Miſtreſs of 'em when you have parted with 'em to a Confident, and your own exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple will juſtify the infidelity which one ought to obſerve in commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nicating his Secrets to another.</p>
            <p n="14">
               <pb n="59" facs="tcp:58078:35"/>14. Once more, renounce and defy all cajolers and flatterers, both the one and t'other deſign by the ſound of their empty diſcourſes, to the Money out of your Pocket, and to raviſh you of your Honour. In fine, the infection of the Plague is not half ſo contagious and fatal for the body, as the Poiſon of Vicious Profligate company; and they that make uſe of Elaborate harangues for no other purpoſe than to enveigle us into a crimi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal <hi>rencoutre</hi> with 'em, employ a perfum'd Poniard to pierce us in the heart.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Behold</hi> Guillemette, <hi>this is it which I had to ſay to you, and which I always deſire you to retain in your Memory, and fearing leſt you might forget it one time or other, I have ſuccinctly digeſted it into particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lars, and committed it to Writing. Be ſure you keep it carefully, and read it often.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <pb n="60" facs="tcp:58078:36"/>
               <hi>Guillemette</hi> made very ſolemn promiſes to obſerve all this, and then they compoſed them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves to reſt till the Morning. The Lady never pared with her out of her company, till ſhe ſaw her in the Coach, ſo that our Lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers cou'd not take their farewel of each other, but only in general terms. Our Marquis having tar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried ſome ſhort time after her, took his leave, and retired to one of his houſes, ſcituated about two Leagues diſtance from the new Habitation of his Miſtreſs, who along with her Companion was very kindly received at her firſt arrival. But the entertainment that followed did not anſwer ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cordingly, for ſhe lived with a Lady whom we ſhall call <hi>Olimpia,</hi> a haughty, imperious, ill-natur'd Woman; that treated all her Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vants after a rude barbarous man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner,
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:58078:36"/>notwithſtanding they uſed the greateſt diligence imaginable in the diſcharge of their duties. This kind of uſage ſeem'd extreme, ly unpalatable to the poor <hi>Guille<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mette;</hi> ſhe was juſt parted from a perſon that had always regarded her as her own Child, whereas ſhe ſaw her ſelf now in a condi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion very little different from that of a Slave, which infinitely diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guſted her, and ſerved to eſtabliſh the Marquis more then ever in her good inclinations. He was now juſt upon the point of deſpair, never a day paſſed over his head, but he rode that way on Horſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>back; yet was never ſo fortunate as to ſee her. At laſt he bethought himſelf of a Stratagem, which accompliſh'd his deſigns. By the vertue of Almighty Money, he gain'd over to his party a certain Peaſant of the Village, that us'd
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:58078:37"/>to furniſh that Caſtle with Fiſh, and made him promiſe to deliver a Letter into the hands of his be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loved <hi>Guillemette;</hi> To prevent all miſtakes, he acquainted him with her Shape and Features, ſo the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther promiſed to perform his part, which he effectually did, for he gave her the Letter. She was ſomewhat diſcompos'd at the manner of receiving it, till the fellow cured her of her fears and apprehenſions, by aſſuring her that he was altogether at the Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiſes devotion. She promiſed to ſend an anſwer by him the day following, ſo the Peaſant made what haſte he could to bring this news to the Marquis, who had all this while impatiently attend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed his return. In the mean time, <hi>Guillemette</hi> open'd the Letter, and read as followeth.</p>
            <floatingText type="letter" xml:lang="eng">
               <body>
                  <pb n="63" facs="tcp:58078:37"/>
                  <opener>
                     <salute>Madam,</salute>
                  </opener>
                  <p>
                     <hi>I</hi> Am perſuaded, that if I did not live entirely for you, I had not been able by this time ſo much as to lift up my Eyes to ſee you without dying. If I cou'd have had the honour to take my leave of you, and know your ſentiments, I had recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved ſufficient conſolation. Do me then the favour that I may enjoy one minute's converſation with you, in ſome place or other: Alas! who cou'd have believed that we ſhould be ſo cruelly ſeparated, when we were juſt upon the point of meeting? However it does not ſignify much, and I have that favourable opinion of your Charity, that it will repair the loſs we have mutually ſuſtain'd. Adieu, my Dear, let me know how matters go with you. You may con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fide entirely in the bearer, for he's truſty and faithful.</p>
               </body>
            </floatingText>
            <pb n="64" facs="tcp:58078:38"/>
            <p>She took no long time in con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſidering of an anſwer. The Let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter found her when ſhe was in a ſuffering condition, and deſirous to be ſet at Liberty, ſo ſhe writ the following anſwer, and dropt it ſlily into the Peaſants Pocket.</p>
            <floatingText type="letter" xml:lang="eng">
               <body>
                  <opener>
                     <salute>Sir,</salute>
                  </opener>
                  <p>ALtho' I have not ſeen you ſince my departure from . . . yet I have not ſuffered that paſſion to be extinguiſhed, which you have kindled in my Heart. For a proof of this let me find you to morrow a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout four a clock diſguis'd in a Fe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>male Habit, on the ſide of the Wood that joyns the High Way; there I ſhall have the Honour to ſee you.</p>
               </body>
            </floatingText>
            <p>Never was the Marquis in ſuch a tranſport of joy, as when he received this Letter, he kiſſed it Twenty times over, and made all
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:58078:38"/>the haſte imaginable, to get his Love Equipage in readineſs. He found her waiting for him on the ſpot, at the hour of Aſſignation, where he ſpoke a thouſand tender paſſionate things to her. She that was now made free and ſociable by the Marquiſes good manage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, complain'd of the haughty carriage of <hi>Olympia,</hi> and of the unworthy uſage wherewith ſhe treated her. He offered her his aſſiſtance immediately to deliver her from this Tyranny; but ſhe would not at firſt conſent to ſuch a motion; deſiring nothing elſe, as ſhe aſſured him, but only to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>late to her former Miſtreſs. But her lover managed his cauſe ſo effectually, by repreſenting to her, that if ſhe followed thoſe meaſures, ſhe would always con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinue in the ſame condition; whereas with him ſhe ſhould be
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:58078:39"/>abſolute Miſtreſs of his fortunes, that ſhe conſented to reſign her ſelf into his hands the Sunday fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowing. He return'd her his thanks with all the Eloquence he was Maſter of, he Embraced her, he Kiſſed her moſt ardently; all this while ſhe ſhew'd nothing of her primitive rigour; ſo that we may conclude, without breach of Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity, that if they had been in a more convenient place, ſhe had ſcarce carried that troubleſome luggage, call'd a Maiden-head, home with her. However, let that paſs, he kiſſed her Eyes, her Mouth, her Neck, her Boſom, and where he pleaſed. This com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plaiſant entertainment of his Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtreſs, threw him into ſuch an extaſie, that he was not able to utter one Syllable, till ſhe thus awaked him. <hi>I fancy,</hi> ſays ſhe, <hi>that I behold you in the very ſame
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:58078:39"/>condition, as you were in the other day, when you were tranſported with a ſudden Spirit of Poetry, becauſe I would not conſent to relieve you with a Kiſs. If that</hi> chagrin, <hi>that ſullen fit of melancholly, which at that time poſſeſſed you, was able to inſpire your Maſe with ſo much vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gour; I am of opinion, that the joy which you teſtify upon this oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſion, ought to produce as lively effects. You are much in the right on't,</hi> replys he, and after he had a little conſidered upon the point, he repeated the following verſes, as he walked by her ſide.</p>
            <q>
               <pb n="68" facs="tcp:58078:40"/>
               <floatingText xml:lang="eng">
                  <body>
                     <div type="ode">
                        <head>An Ode upon a KISS.</head>
                        <lg n="1">
                           <head>I.</head>
                           <l>NAy, now Ambitious thoughts farewell,</l>
                           <l>I pity Kings in all their ſtate,</l>
                           <l>While thus in <hi>Sylvia</hi>'s arms I dwell,</l>
                           <l>And mighty love does on my triumphs wait.</l>
                        </lg>
                        <lg n="2">
                           <head>II.</head>
                           <l>Thus let me languiſhing expire,</l>
                           <l>Encircled in her Snowy Arms,</l>
                           <l>Till ſhe revives me by her Charms,</l>
                           <l>And pours into my breaſt a new and nobler fire.</l>
                        </lg>
                        <lg n="3">
                           <head>III.</head>
                           <l>Thus let me Kiſs my Soul away,</l>
                           <l>And revel in ſubſtantial bliſs;</l>
                           <l>Thus let me ſpend the fleeting day,</l>
                           <l>And crown each beauteous moment with a Kiſs.</l>
                        </lg>
                        <lg n="4">
                           <head>IV.</head>
                           <l>
                              <hi>Adonis</hi> ne're was half ſo bleſt,</l>
                           <l>Was ne're ſo fortunate as I:</l>
                           <l>Tho' Loves bright Goddeſs him careſt,</l>
                           <l>And in her Arms hugg'd the delicious Boy.</l>
                        </lg>
                        <lg n="5">
                           <pb n="69" facs="tcp:58078:40"/>
                           <head>V.</head>
                           <l>Nor <hi>Jove</hi> himſelf ſuch tranſports knew,</l>
                           <l>When <hi>Danae</hi> the amorous God did hold:</l>
                           <l>Tho' he, the pleaſure to purſue,</l>
                           <l>Mortgag'd his poor Almighty-ſhip to Gold.</l>
                        </lg>
                        <lg n="6">
                           <head>VI.</head>
                           <l>Ten thouſand loves in pompous ſtate</l>
                           <l>On thoſe two Roſy Lips. reſide:</l>
                           <l>While buſy I with erger pride</l>
                           <l>Sip all the ſweets of love, and bleſs my happy fate.</l>
                        </lg>
                        <lg n="7">
                           <head>VII.</head>
                           <l>Now on her glowing breaſt I range,</l>
                           <l>Now kiſs her Cheeks, and now her Eyes.</l>
                           <l>The pleaſure's heighten'd by the change,</l>
                           <l>And fills my Senfes with immortal joys.</l>
                        </lg>
                        <lg n="8">
                           <head>VIII.</head>
                           <l>But Ah! my beauteous Nymph, beware,</l>
                           <l>Ho<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                                 <desc>•</desc>
                              </gap> you encreaſe my ſtore:</l>
                           <l>For elſe your pamper'd Slave may dare,</l>
                           <l>Drunk as he is with joy, to ſue for ſomething more.</l>
                        </lg>
                        <lg n="9">
                           <head>IX.</head>
                           <l>For ſay fond Lovers, what you will,</l>
                           <l>To deify a Kiſs:</l>
                           <l>'Tis but a pledge or prologue ſtill,</l>
                           <l>An earneſt to ſecure the great ſucceeding bliſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                                 <desc>•</desc>
                              </gap>.</l>
                        </lg>
                     </div>
                  </body>
               </floatingText>
            </q>
            <p>
               <pb n="70" facs="tcp:58078:41"/>After he had thus concluded, he let a ſigh drop from him, and ſaid, Well, Madam, what think you of this Poetical tranſport now, have you enough of it? Yes in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed, ſays ſhe, and I here proteſt to you, that I like theſe Verſes extremely well. If it were poſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble for me to have a greater eſteem for you than I have already, it would be, becauſe you have ſo extraordinary a Genius at Poetry: Nothing cou'd contribute to ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vance you higher in my good opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion than that. To confeſs the truth, I have a mighty paſſion and reſpect for Poets, and all per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons of underſtanding, as I con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive, ought to preſerve the ſame veneration for them. I am ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſh'd with joy, Madam, ſays the Marquis, that I am Maſter of any good Qualities, that are capable of giving you a diverſion: I aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:58078:41"/>you, My deareſt, that I ſhall take care to cultivate this poor <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>alent of mine, ſince I find you have a kindneſs for it, and that nothing of Gallantry ſhall paſs be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween us, which I ſhall not endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour to give you an account of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>n Verſe. Upon my word, an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwers ſhe, you will infinitely ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ige me by ſo doing. After they had ſaid abundance of amorous <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>hings one to another, and had reaſon'd ſufficiently upon this Subject, they parted with a pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe not to fail meeting at the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>our of Aſſignation. Immediately when ſhe was return'd back to her Chamber, ſhe began to make ſome reflections upon this affair; and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>s ſhe was accidentally looking for ſome thing or other in her Trunk, ſhe chanced at the ſame <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ime to lay her hands on the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtructions, that were formerly
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:58078:42"/>given her by the old Lady. She read 'em over not without ſome uneaſineſs, and qualms of conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, becauſe ſhe ſaw her actions ſo apparently blamed in 'em: But to what purpoſe? She had had already given her promiſe, and the intrigue was too far ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vanced to think of making a re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treat. But on the other ſide, the Inſtructions carried reaſon and weight in 'em, ſhe was going to embarque her ſelf in an affair, which perhaps might coſt her a great deal of repentance, when it would be too late, and what ſhould a poor perplexed Damoſel do in ſuch an intricate, mortify<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing caſe? She found out, at laſt, the true expedient, which was to ſacrifice theſe troubleſome inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions to the flames, that ſhe might have nothing about her to refreſh her Memory, or reproach
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:58078:42"/>her proceedings. So now, Gentle Reader, you may imagine the pious <hi>Gullemette</hi> committing the help<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs criminal Papers to the Fire, and aftewards very devoutly ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king her repoſe. The fatal Sun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>day now approached; therefore ſhe made all the haſte ſhe could to pack up the beſt of her move<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ables in a little bundle, and at the time appointed ſhe took 'em under her Arm, and marched out of the Caſtle, without being per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived by any body. Within two hundred paces of the place, ſhe found her truſty Lover, who at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended her coming in a Coach and Six Horſes; they took her up, and made ſuch ſpeed that in leſs then two hours, they arrived at his Houſe; He had prepared a magnificent Apartment for her reception; In fine, he paſſed a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way the Night with her, and ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſh'd
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:58078:43"/>that flower from her, which the men ſearch after with ſo much curioſity, and the Women ought ſo induſtriouſly to preſerve and guard. In the mean time, they miſſed her at the Caſtle, and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieved ſhe was return'd back again to her old Quarters. They pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſently diſpatched a Meſſenger thi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther to enquire after her, but ſhe was not to be found; the old La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy was exceedingly afflicted at the news, and as for her part <hi>O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lympia</hi> left nothing unattempted to diſcover whether ſhe was Aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaſſinated or no. All this while, they could not imagine what was become of her, and we have reaſon to ſuppoſe, that it had been a long time before they had received a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny intelligence, where ſhe reſided, if one of the old Ladies Servants, that was ſent to the Marquis up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on an Errand, had not by mere
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:58078:43"/>accident ſpy'd her looking out of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> Window. He did not ſeem to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>iſcover any manner of aſtoniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment at the ſight, but ſhe no ſoon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er perceived him, but ſhe im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mediately retired to the other end <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>f her Chamber; as ſoon as he <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ame home, he declared the whole matter to the good Lady, who <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>om the beginning teſtify'd a <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>reat deal of ſorrow upon this oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſion, but now comforted her <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>elf to hear that <hi>Guillemette</hi> was <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>live. Nevertheleſs, ſhe baniſhed <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>e poor Marquis for ever from <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>er Houſe, and would not per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>it him to ſee her any more. For <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ll that, he did not in the leaſt for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ear to paſs his time as agreeably <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> he could with his beloved Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>reſs; and becauſe he remembred <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>mſelf, that ſhe loved Poetry, he <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>iled not to divert her even that <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ay, as often as their gallantry
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:58078:44"/>furniſh'd him with an occaſion.</p>
            <p>She found all his compoſitions very agreeable and natural, and took a great deal of pleaſure in reading 'em over. She pay'd the Marquis for his Poetry in the ſame Coyn, as ſhe pay'd him in for all the other civilities ſhe received at his hands. Thus according to appearances, they paſſed their time contentedly enough, their mutual affection continued very warm and violent for a conſider<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able ſpace, and all the while this happy couple never troubled their heads with any other matters. The Marquis made a journy to the Court, after which he returned home, fuller of Love and Vigour than before; much about this time the Judge of one of the prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipal Villages belonging to the Marquis, became a Widdower, and he immediately thought of
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:58078:44"/>ſupplying that place for him, with his <hi>Guillemette;</hi> he was a very honeſt plain man, very rich, and very young; but the difficulty was to know whether the Judge would ſit down contented with another man's leavings, and ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit the long Robe to the lubrici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty and levity of a Woman. How<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever, he was in good hopes to gain him, ſo for this purpoſe he communicated the deſign to <hi>Guil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lemette,</hi> and repreſented to her, that it would prove a very advan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tageous match, that it would re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pair her honour, and not in the leaſt deſtroy or interrupt their correſpondence. For in fine, my deareſt, ſays he to her, 'tis only for thy Intereſt that I attempt this affair; and don't believe that I have a mind to abandon thee. No, I'le ſooner abandon my whole Eſtate, and I ſhould be happy e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough
<pb n="78" facs="tcp:58078:45"/>in the ſole poſſeſſion o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> thee, to make the greateſt Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>narchs envy my condition, tho<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> I was diveſted of all my other for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tunes. 'Tis therefore for thy good only that I undertake this enter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prize, and that we may continue our intrigues with the greater pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vacy and ſecurity. If you are of opinion that it will be for your advantage, we'l joyntly employ our efforts to wheedle him into the oval of Matrimony. She was convinced with the force of his arguments, and return'd him a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bundance of thanks for all his care, and civilities; promiſing to make uſe of all her Charms to draw this Pigeon to her Pigeon-houſe, but they were well match'd, he was the Devil of a Rat, and ſhe was the Devil of a Cat.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="79" facs="tcp:58078:45"/>The Marquis frequently invited the Judge to dine with him, he frequently complained before him of the loſs of his Lady, he often regal'd him at his Table; and gave him all the marks of friend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip imaginable, and all this while the poor Judge knew not one Syl<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lable of the true occaſion. <hi>Guille<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mette</hi> alſo frequently entertain'd him in particular, when the Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quis was call'd away by other company. Never did Veſtal Vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gin ſhew more Prudence and Pi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ety than ſhe made appear in all her converſation and behaviour; they that were not acquainted with her Character, would have infallibly taken her for a Second <hi>Lucretia.</hi> In the mean time, the Marquis ſounded by little and lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle the Judges Sentiments, about a Second Marriage, he diſcourſed <hi>en paſſant</hi> of this affair daily to
<pb n="80" facs="tcp:58078:46"/>him; but to all this he return'd no clear poſitive anſwers, but talked all the while ambiguouſly. But one day, our Marquis was reſolved to ſound his inclinations for good and all; to this end, af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter dinner was over, he took him out to walk with him in one of the Parters of his Garden, and thus open'd himſelf: You know, Sir, the eſtimation I have always made of your Perſon, I have di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinguiſh'd you from all the Juſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciaries of my Precincts, to place you in theſe circumſtances; the more I find I have for you a cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain honeſt, well-meaning, com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plaiſant tenderneſs, that obliges me to have a great reſpect and concern for your wellfare. This is the reaſon why I paſſionately deſire to ſee you advantageouſly placed in a Second Marriage, and upon this ſcore I have a great de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire
<pb n="81" facs="tcp:58078:46"/>to marry you from my own hands. The Judge thanked him very ſubmiſſively for all the fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vours he had received of him; and particularly for the honour he did him daily at his Houſe. But, Sir, ſays he, you have talked to me concerning a certain thing, of which I have not entertain'd the leaſt thoughts ſince the death of my Wife; I don't queſtion but that coming from your hands, ſhe muſt be a perſon that has abun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dance of merit, and honour: but may a man be ſo happy as to know who this Lady is? 'Tis that young Gentlewoman, replies the Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quis, that you have ſo often ſeen at my houſe; ſhe was given me for the Governant of my Family, and I muſt freely own to you, that I have a great eſteem for her ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tues. She's a perſon of Wit and good underſtanding; and beſides
<pb n="82" facs="tcp:58078:47"/>her other qualifications, ſhe'l have four thouſand Livres by way of Portion, which I intend to beſtow upon her; beſides, the firſt va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cant place that falls in the Court of Judicature, at <hi>Poictiers,</hi> which I offer you to accept of, as you find convenient.</p>
            <p>The Judge was not at all igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant of the train that was laid for him; and as ſoon as he heard the name of <hi>Guillemette</hi> mention'd, he ſmelt the deſign, and imme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diately formed a reſolution in him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf not to comply with his Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tron's inclinations. But as it was his intereſt to manage <hi>Monſieur le Marquis</hi> as dexterouſly as he cou'd, he was not willing on the ſudden to give him a total refuſal, not at all queſtioning, but that the other, who carefully obſerved all his actions, would conclude from his rejecting the offer, that he had
<pb n="83" facs="tcp:58078:47"/>ſome intelligence of their deſigns upon him. Therefore he took the midle way; and after he had complemented the Marquis upon the ſcore of all his favours and civilities, he humbly repreſented to him, that an affair of that im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portance, as Marriage, ought to be nicely conſider'd, before one throws himſelf into it; that with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in five days at fartheſt he ſhould receive his anſwer in writing, where he would take the liberty to expreſs his Sentiments ſincere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, in caſe he ſhould not be able to accept the party. The Marquis preſſed him to explain himſelf more clearly upon this point, but without any effect; He only re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iterated his former promiſe, ſo that the Marquis was obliged to content himſelf with it, and went immediately to carry the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>Guillemette,</hi> who no ſooner <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="84" facs="tcp:58078:48"/>it, but ſhe preſaged ill ſucceſs to her ſelf in the matter. Neverthe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs they expected the anſwer, and accordingly it came to their hands at the prefixed time, they had the curioſity to know what Myſteries the Paper contain'd within; ſo they broke it open, and read as follows.</p>
            <floatingText type="letter" xml:lang="eng">
               <body>
                  <opener>
                     <salute>Sir,</salute>
                  </opener>
                  <p>AFter having made abandance of reflections upon the incon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ventences and misfortunes, that Marriage generally carries along with it, I have taken up a reſolution not to venture my ſelf the ſecond time on that outragious Sea, but to paſs the remainder of my Life in ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curity in the Harbour. The moſt convincing arguments that ſerved to determine my opinion in this caſe, were ſent me in a Letter by a Poet, a Friend of mine: I have tranſcrib'd
<pb n="85" facs="tcp:58078:48"/>a copy of 'em for you, that you may ſee the advice which he gives me, and with what an invincible aver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion be declaims againſt Matrimony. In the mean time, I ſhall never ceaſe to make you all the acknowledgments in the World for your infinite fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vours, and I am heartily diſpleas'd with my ſelf, that I cannot force my inclination ſo far, as to offer my Vows to that charming perſon you deſign'd for me. You may rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonably believe, that Providence never deſign'd me for ſo great a bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing, however I ſhall always reſerve that honour of Writing my ſelf,</p>
                  <closer>
                     <signed>Your, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                     </signed>
                  </closer>
               </body>
            </floatingText>
            <q>
               <pb n="86" facs="tcp:58078:49"/>
               <floatingText xml:lang="eng">
                  <body>
                     <div type="poem">
                        <head>Advice about MARRIAGE.</head>
                        <l>THe Husband's the Pilot, the Wife is the Ocean,</l>
                        <l>He's always in Danger, ſhe always in Motion.</l>
                        <l>And he that in Wedlock twice hazards his Carkaſs,</l>
                        <l>Twice ventures a drowning; and faith that's an hard Caſe:</l>
                        <l>Ev'n at our Weapons the Female defeat us,</l>
                        <l>And death, only death can ſign our <hi>Quietus.</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>Not to tell you ſad Stories of Liberty loſt</l>
                        <l>How our Joys are all pall'd, and our Plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſures all croſt,</l>
                        <l>This Pagan Confinement, this damnable Station,</l>
                        <l>Suits no Order, nor Age, nor Degree in the Nation.</l>
                        <l>The <hi>Levite</hi> it keeps from Parochial Duty,</l>
                        <l>For who can at once mind Religion and Beauty?</l>
                        <l>The rich it Alarms with Expences and trouble,</l>
                        <l>And a poor Beaſt you know, will ſcarce carry double.</l>
                        <l>
                           <pb n="87" facs="tcp:58078:49"/>Twas invented, they ſay, to keep us from falling,</l>
                        <l>Oh the Virtue and Grace of aſhril Catter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wauling!</l>
                        <l>But it pales in your Game. Ay, but how do you know, Sir,</l>
                        <l>How often your Neighbour breaks up the Encloſure.</l>
                        <l>For this is the principal comfort of Mariage,</l>
                        <l>You muſt eat, tho' a hundred has ſpit in your Porrige.</l>
                        <l>True Woman nere minds a Sermon, or Lecture,</l>
                        <l>Her Glaſs is her Guide, and her Ghostly director,</l>
                        <l>Then ſhe Primes her gay Looks, with an early Devotion,</l>
                        <l>There ſhe Paints, and ſhe Patches, and ſtudies each Motion.</l>
                        <l>Not to pleaſe the dull ſight of her Conjugal Satyr,</l>
                        <l>But charm and confound ev'ry gaping Spectator.</l>
                        <l>If at Night you're unactive, and fail of performing,</l>
                        <l>Enter Thunder, and Lightning, and Blood<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed next Morning.</l>
                        <l>Crys the bone of your ſide, thanks dear Mr. Horner.</l>
                        <l>
                           <pb n="88" facs="tcp:58078:50"/>This comes of your ſinning with Crape in a Corner.</l>
                        <l>Then to make up the breach, all your might you muſt Rally,</l>
                        <l>And Labour, and Sweat like a Slave at the Gally.</l>
                        <l>Yet ſtill you muſt Charge, Oh Bleſſed Condition!</l>
                        <l>Tho you know to your coſt, you've no more Ammunition.</l>
                        <l>Till at laſt, my dear mortified Tool of a Man.</l>
                        <l>You're not able to make a poor flaſh in the Pan.</l>
                        <l>Fire, Female, and Flood begin with a Letter,</l>
                        <l>And the Worlds for them all ſcarce a Far<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing the better.</l>
                        <l>The Flood ſoon is gone, and your Fire you may humble,</l>
                        <l>If into the Flames ſtore of water you tumble,</l>
                        <l>But the Fire of a Female, on the word of a Friend,</l>
                        <l>Is ne'r to be quench'd, but burns World without end.</l>
                        <l>
                           <pb n="89" facs="tcp:58078:50"/>You may call half the Engines, and pumps in the Nation,</l>
                        <l>To extinguiſh the Flame, and allay Titula<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</l>
                        <l>But may Piſs out as well the laſt Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flagration.</l>
                        <l>Thus Sir, I have ſent you my thoughts of the Matter,</l>
                        <l>Judge you as you pleaſe, but I ſcorn to Flatter.</l>
                     </div>
                  </body>
               </floatingText>
            </q>
            <p>The Marquis was very ſorry, that his Project met with no bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter Succeſs; in the mean time the two Lovers did what they could, to comfort one another, by a Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinuation of their Amours.</p>
            <q>
               <l>But as reſiſtance feeds the Flame,</l>
               <l>And fans the dying Fire.</l>
               <l>So dull Enjoyments ſpoils the Game,</l>
               <l>By palling the deſire.</l>
            </q>
            <p>In effect, our Marquis alſo, like he reſt of his Sex, began to for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>get
<pb n="90" facs="tcp:58078:51"/>get his Promiſes; for he apparent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly neglected her, and never looked upon her without a certain ſpice of Melancholy. Nevertheleſs ſhe was happy enough, in having poſſeſſed him for about the ſpace of ten years, after which time was ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpired, ſeeing that he had not that Eſteem for her, as he formerly had, but on the contrary negle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted her, ſhe reſolved with her ſelf to leave him, ſo ſhe begged leave of him to depart, but he pretended at firſt, by way of Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plement, an extream unwilling<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs to part with her, but at laſt, he gave her his Conſent, and to ſay the Truth without any great importunity. She had got to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether, what by her own ſav<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings, and what by the Preſents the Marquis made her, a pretty Sum of Money, with which ſhe took her way towards <hi>Paris.</hi>
               <pb n="91" facs="tcp:58078:51"/>When ſhe arrived there, ſhe lived after a high profuſe rate, not be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing able to diſ-accuſtom her to thoſe fine Dainties, ſhe uſed to eat at the Marquis's Table. But as every thing is dear at <hi>Paris,</hi> ſhe was obliged to retrench her Expences, and conſider of ſome Livelihood or other, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by to ſupport her ſelf. For this purpoſe ſhe entreated a virtuous Old Matron, who made it her buſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs to promote a civil Correſpon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence between the two Sexes, and bring good People together, to put her in a way; but this pru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent Gentlewoman ſeeing her young, and beautiful enough, propoſed a Match to her, as the moſt probable, and advantageous Courſe to make her Fortune. She was not very averſe to the Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and preſently inquired af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter the Perſon, and his Vocation;
<pb n="92" facs="tcp:58078:52"/>to this ſhe received Anſwer, that his Name was <hi>Monſieur Scaron,</hi> and that he was of the honoura<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Society of Poets. The Name of a Poet raviſhed her Soul with Joy, ſhe longed to ſee him im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mediately, but the Old Woman judging it convenient to prepare before her before hand, for ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſo extraordinary a Figure, and to give her ſome ſhort Deſcrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of his Perſon, leaſt ſhe ſhould be affrighted at the ſight of him, thus began her Diſcourſe. <hi>Like my dear Child with reverence and attention, I am very willing to oblige you with a ſhort Portraiture of this Gentleman before you go to ſee him. In the firſt place, he's young, of an ordinary Stature, but very de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed; his Legs, his Head and his Body in the poſture as they are Scituate, make the exact Repreſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation of a Z. His Eyes are ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>what
<pb n="93" facs="tcp:58078:52"/>of the largeſt, but ſunk into his Head; his Noſe is true</hi> Roman, <hi>his Teeth of the ſame Colour with Ebory, and very irregularly placed; his Members to outward appearance ſeem ſmall and ſlender, I mean his vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible Members, for I don't deſire to be underſtood of the reſt; however to make amends for this want of Sym<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>metry and Proportion, he has an infinite deal of Wit above the reſt of Mankind; to recommend him farther to you, he has ſomething to live upon, he has a Penſion from the Court, and is the Son of a Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tleman of the Long robe; at preſent if you have a mind to ſee him, we'l go and make him a Viſit.</hi> She a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greed to the propoſal, and ſo they went; <hi>Scaron</hi> who had ſome in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formation of their coming, had dreſſed himſelf up like a <hi>Bartholo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mew</hi>-Baby, and attended them in his Chair; at their entring into
<pb n="94" facs="tcp:58078:53"/>the Room. <hi>Scaron</hi> received them with all the Civility imaginable, and for her part <hi>Guillemette</hi> endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voured to anſwer him in like manner, but not without laugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to ſee ſo Comical, and pleaſant a Figure. Their Converſation having laſted almoſt the ſpace of an hour, they took their leaves of him, and the Old Woman en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaged her ſelf ſeveral times to bring <hi>Guillemette</hi> along with her again: They made him a Second Vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſit, when he entertained them with a ſmall regale of a Collation, and and the venerable Matron being gone out to look after ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing which ſhe had loſt, <hi>Scaron</hi> began to diſplay the Charms of his Wit, and diſcovered his Paſſion to the adorable <hi>Guillemette.</hi> He told her, that he very well con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jectured, that a Lady ſo beauti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful and handſome as ſhe, would
<pb n="95" facs="tcp:58078:53"/>not willingly Embarras her ſelf with ſuch a demy Monſter as he was. <hi>But Madam, notwithſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing all this Diſcouragement,</hi> ſays he, <hi>if I durſt lay any manner of va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lue upon my ſelf, I would tell you, that this ill favorable Tabernacle of mine, for all it Promiſes ſo little, perhaps lodges a Spirit in it, that de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerves a better Caſe, and that is ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tremely concerned to find it ſelf in Company with thoſe Perſons, who are ſo advantagiouſly provided with all the Gifts of Nature. As for my ſelf, I can aſſure you, Madam, that I ſhall be always obliged to treat you with the profoundeſt reſpect, in caſe I ſhall have the Happineſs to be ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proved by you: But give me leave to tell you, Madam, that delays are not convenient upon theſe occaſions.</hi> As ſhe was going to anſwer him, one of <hi>Scaron</hi>'s Siſters entred the Room, which made her reſerve
<pb n="96" facs="tcp:58078:54"/>till another time, what ſhe had to ſay, ſo that then ſhe did not ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plain her ſelf upon this ſubject, but at the next viſit ſhe made him, well had this old Matron acquitted her ſelf of her com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion, that ſhe plainly promiſed him to be his Wife. He was immediately inſpired with the greateſt joy in the World; and after this happy declaration he never failed to entertain her day<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly with his <hi>Billets doux,</hi> which he compoſed ſo agreeably, that they ſerved not a little to conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nue her in the ſame favourable ſentiments.</p>
            <p>But Oh! the Fates, this com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plaiſant humour did not ſtay with her long, for there happen'd a ſmall rupture between the Lovers. The Old Matron went into the Country to accommodate a cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain affair of mighty conſequence
<pb n="97" facs="tcp:58078:54"/>to her, but all this while the ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>durate <hi>Guillemette</hi> continued firm in her reſolution, and ſwore ſhe would never ſee, or think of him any more. When the door <hi>Scaron</hi> underſtood this ill news, he en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dured all thoſe vexations which deſpair uſes to inſpire us with, and his grief was yet the more and more violent, when he heard that ſhe rejected all his Letters. He and his truſty confident were juſt upon the point of accompliſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing their deſigns, and now to be defeated, when they fancied they had ſurmounted all difficulties, was a mortification not to be ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſt: But <hi>Scaron,</hi> that was maſter of a great deal of Wit, happily remembred himſelf, that ſhe loved verſes exceedingly, and took an inſpeakable pleaſure to her him repeat ſome of his Poetry. There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore he reſolved to attempt her
<pb n="98" facs="tcp:58078:55"/>once more that way, and wrote abundance of Billets to her in this faſhion. After ſhe had read them over, ſhe decently laid 'em aſide, as ſhe had done the reſt, but wou'd not condeſcend to return him any anſwer. Nevertheleſs, our inde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fatigable lover charged her daily with his amorous Epiſtles; his conſtancy, his reſpectful behavi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our; to which were added the aſſiduities of his Confidence, fail'd not at long run to re-eſtabliſh him in his Miſtreſſes good graces. But he, that was very well acquainted with the inconſtancy of the Age, did not think it <hi>á propos</hi> to ſpend much time in this affair; there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore he preſſed her with all the ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guments he could Summon on this occaſion; and, in fine, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>new'd his importunities with that ſucceſs, that in a ſhort time the Marriage was conſummated be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween
<pb n="99" facs="tcp:58078:55"/>'em. But alaſs, poor Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tleman! he found himſelf migh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tily miſtaken in his judgment; and what he imagined would be the conſolation of his Life, pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved juſt the contrary. He found a large Breach made ready to his hands, through which the Lord knows how many combatants had mounted to make the Aſſault. He complained of this ſame buſineſs to her; but ſhe was ſo far from denying the matter, that ſhe told him in an imperious tone, that it was not for ſuch a feeble, meagre, two-legg'd figure, as he was, to have the entire poſſeſſion of ſuch a Woman as her ſelf; and that he ought to reckon himſelf happy enough in all conſcience, that ſhe was able to ſuffer his nauſeous embraces. This unwelcome diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe; which he expected no more than a Summons to the next
<pb n="100" facs="tcp:58078:56"/>World, reduced him to the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tremity of deſpair; and foraſmuch as it lay exceeding heavy upon him, he was willing to diſcharge in into the hands of one of his Siſters, not at all believing that he cou'd diſpoſe of the Secret to a better Perſon; or that ſhe wou'd take pains to publiſh the infamy of her own Family: but he found himſelf exceedingly miſtaken, to imagine, that one of the frailer Sex was capable of concealing ſo nice and critical a ſecret; howe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver, at laſt, he diſcovered his grievances to her, after he had mightily aggravated the conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quence of this affair, and told her how tenderly it concerned his Life and Reputation to have it kept private. She failed not on her ſide to ſwear and promiſe e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very thing in the World, which he would have her do, out of an
<pb n="101" facs="tcp:58078:56"/>itching deſire ſhe had to be made acquainted with this important matter. But ſhe no ſooner under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtood what it was, but ſhe found her ſelf poſſeſs'd with a far grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter inclination to diſcloſe it. Thus ſhe continued for ſome days in this Female irreſolution, ſaying and unſaying the very ſame thing. One day for inſtance, ſhe fell into the following tranſport.</p>
            <q>
               <lg>
                  <l>There's no body knows this ſecret, but I.</l>
                  <l>Which I've heartily ſworn to conceal <hi>par ma foy:</hi>
                  </l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>And I've promis'd, without any damn'd reſerva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion,</l>
                  <l>Not to utter one Word to a Soul in the Nation.</l>
                  <l>Then muſt I conceal it? Alaſs and alack!</l>
                  <l>I may promiſe as well to bear <hi>Pauls</hi> on my back.</l>
                  <l>But then if I tell is, I ruin my Brother.</l>
                  <l>Why Iſaith I can't help it, as well he as another.</l>
                  <l>This telling of Secrets is part of our Charter,</l>
                  <l>And for my part, I ſwear, I'le dye no body's martyr.</l>
                  <l>Well, let me conſider once more of the matter.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Either burn or diſcloſe it, why troth chuſe the latter.</l>
                  <l>But then if I ſpeak it, forewell reputation,</l>
                  <l>And beſides I may raiſe his ſevere indignation,</l>
                  <l>But what Woman alive can conceal fornication?</l>
                  <l>
                     <pb n="102" facs="tcp:58078:57"/>Not a female on Earth can Cuckoldom ſmother,</l>
                  <l>Then don't take it ill from your Siſter good Brother.</l>
                  <l>You know what the Matron ſaid unto her Daughter,</l>
                  <l>Ne're long keep a Secret, nor long hold your Water.</l>
               </lg>
            </q>
            <p>After ſo many different agita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, ſheoeſolved at laſt to put her ſelf out of this torment, and communicate the ſecred to a truſty She-friend of hers; this truſty Female handed it to another, and ſhe likewiſe to her next Neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour, and ſo on to the end of the Chapter, till at laſt, the whole Town was acquainted with the Secret, and the greateſt part of the converſation in the city went to this Tune. However as every thing in the World has its time, ſo ſome new accident or other, occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion'd even this diſcourſe to va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſh; but this did not afford the leaſt comfort to the Unfortunate <hi>Scaron,</hi> but the oft ner he reflected on the cruelty of his Stars, and
<pb n="103" facs="tcp:58078:57"/>the unhappineſs of his condition, he found his Melancholly humour to grow upon him. In fine, he was ſo ſenſibly affected with re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>morſe of conſcience for what he had done, that it made him paſs the remainder of his Life in a ſad languiſhing condition, and at laſt carried him out of the World. His pious Wife, according to the laudable cuſtom of the World, for ſome time appeared very de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolate and afflicted, as you know good manners and civility obliged her to do. She ſubſiſted for a while upon the ſmall for tune that her Husband had left her, for Poets are ſeldom guilty of leaving great Sums behind 'em; but being ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfied that her poor ſtock would not laſt for ever, ſhe reſolved to purſue her firſt deſign, and look after a Service. Never was a more favourable opportunity preſented
<pb n="104" facs="tcp:58078:58"/>to her then now; ſhe had the luck to meet with one of her old companions of <hi>Poitou,</hi> who was ſo happy as to be placed in a very advantageous ſtation with Madam <hi>de Monteſpan.</hi> This honeſt ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quaintance promiſed to employ her utmoſt intereſt with her Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtreſs, to get her fixed in ſome good condition; and at laſt ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeded in her endeavours, for ſhe procured her a Governants place in the houſe of a Perſon of Qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity; but this was in <hi>Portugal,</hi> and thither ſhe was obliged to tranſport her ſelf, if ſhe complied with the Motion. She agreed to to it with all her heart; and du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring the time that the Perſons with whom ſhe was to live, were making preparations for their Voy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>age, ſhe went frequently to Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dam <hi>de Monteſpan</hi>'s, to thank her ſhe companion for the kindneſs ſhe
<pb n="105" facs="tcp:58078:58"/>had done her; and likewiſe to endeavour if it were poſſible to have audience of this celebrated favourite before ſhe departed. This favour ſhe obtained by the means of her correſpondent, and acquitted her ſelf ſo agreeably in her converſation before the above-mention'd Madam <hi>de Monteſpan,</hi> that ſhe deſired to ſee her often. Not to be tedious, ſhe pleas'd her ſo extremely with the gayety of her diſeourſe, that this Lady ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gining ſhe might be uſeful to her upon ſeveral occaſions, was wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling to entertain her in her Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice; and having obliged her to break off her deſign'd Voyage to <hi>Portugal,</hi> kept her in her Family: Where ſhe inſinuated her ſelf ſo dexterouſly into her good opinion, that in a-ſhort time ſhe became her only Confident. Nothing was now to be done with the King,
<pb n="106" facs="tcp:58078:59"/>but by the favour of <hi>Monteſpan,</hi> and nothing with her, but through the interceſſion of Madam <hi>Scaron:</hi> She managed her good fortune with that addreſs and policy, that ſhe has never ſince ſuffer'd any alteration in it; on the contrary the favour ſhe found with her Miſtreſs, brought her daily a vaſt quantity of preſents, and particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>larly there happen'd an opportu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity of conſiderable importance to her, which ſerved as well to make her carry the cauſe, as to inform the World what intereſt and power ſhe had in the very be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginning of her Elevation, which has encreas'd to her advantage ever ſince.</p>
            <p>The King's Chief Phyſician be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing dead, his Majeſty reſolved to accept of no body for favour or affection, but to chuſe one him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf; and in order to ſupply that
<pb n="107" facs="tcp:58078:59"/>conſiderable place, began to caſt an Eye upon Monſieur <hi>Vallot.</hi> We may reaſonably enough con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clude that he had carried it, if death had not raviſhed him out of the World. Immediate upon his deceaſe, there appeared a great number of Competitors upon the Stage; who durſt never have made any pretenſions to the place, if <hi>Vallot</hi> had been living. Every one employ'd the interceſſion and prayers of his Friends to ſucceed in his deſign; but all theſe entrea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tres were to no purpoſe; a requeſt of this nature, without a good handſom gift to recommend it, carries but little efficacy along with it. The truth of this aſſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion was ſoon underſtood by thoſe pretenders, who were not over and above furniſh'd in the Pocket; and they ſaw clearly that it was but time and labour loſt to make
<pb n="108" facs="tcp:58078:60"/>any further buſtle. Monſieur <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quin</hi> was the man that found the eaſieſt acceſs, for he thonght it a piece of imprudence to ſtarve a good cauſe, and only to depend on a few feeble ſimple Petitions; ſo he went a ſurer way to work, and promiſed Madam <hi>Scaron</hi> to make her a purſe of twenty thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand Crowns, in caſe ſhe helped him to the place. This was too tempting and advantageous an offer to be refuſed; therefore ſhe uſed all the ways ſhe could think of, to bring <hi>Monteſpan</hi> to her par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty; ſhe employ'd her utmoſt ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forts to accompliſh the deſign, and did not conceal from her, the advantage ſhe was to make, if this affair ſucceeded. <hi>Monteſpan</hi> who loved her exceedingly, was not ſorry to find an occaſion to gain her ſuch a conſiderable Sum as this; to this effect, ſhe made
<pb n="109" facs="tcp:58078:60"/>uſe of all her Intereſt with the King: In ſhort, her Petition met with ſucceſs, and ſhe obtained this pretty round Sum of Money for our Heroine, who to teſtify her acknowledgments for ſo tranſcen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dant a favour, redoubled her dili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gence about her, in ſuch a man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner, that it was almoſt impoſſible for <hi>Monteſpan</hi> to ſuffer any one elſe about her. It was ſhe that kept all her Soctets, and into her hands ſhe made no ſcruple or dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficulty to commit thoſe Letters which the King wrote to her; nay ſometimes ſhe made uſe of her aſſiſtance to anſwer 'em. One day ſhe compoſed ſo charming, ſo accurate, and tender a <hi>Billet,</hi> that the King, who has a delicate apprehenſion and penetration in theſe matters, ſoon perceived that it was infinitely above the Cenius of his Miſtreſs; he pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſently
<pb n="110" facs="tcp:58078:61"/>preſently reſolved to enform him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf from what hand it came, and began at the ſame time, to enter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain ſomeſuſpicious thoughts, ſome little motions of Jealouſie, that ſomething had happen'd which would prove fatal to his Amour. Being come to Madam <hi>de Monteſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pan</hi>'s apartment, he told her, he was deſirous to know what per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons had dictated that Letter; for as for you your ſelf, Madam, ſays he, I have known you long enough to be ſufficiently acquainted with your Style, and way of Writing. Therefore tell me without any reſerve or diſguife, who it is. Since you muſt needs oblige me to tell you, anſwers ſhe, I will do it, tho' I am confident you'l find it a difficult matter to believe it. But not to keep your mind any longer in ſuſpenſe, 'twas Madam <hi>Scaron</hi> that dictated the Letter, and I
<pb n="111" facs="tcp:58078:61"/>tranſcrib'd it from hers; and that your Majeſty may not in the leaſt doubt of the verity of what I have ſaid, I'le go fetch the Original un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der her own hand. In ſhort, ſhe brought it, and proſented it to him. The King was very well ſatis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fy'd with it, and demanded to ſee Mademoiſelle <hi>Searon,</hi> who at that juncture of time was not to be found: But ſhortly after, as ſhe happen'd to be with Madam <hi>de Monteſpan,</hi> the King entred the room; ſhe was going to with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>draw out of reſpect to his Majeſty, but he would not permit her to quit the place; and gave her a thouſand commendations for the happy talent ſhe had in wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting of Letters. She anſwered e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very thing he ſaid to her with ſo much flame and Gallantry, that he admired her more and more, and began to diſtinguiſh her from
<pb n="112" facs="tcp:58078:62"/>his other Domeſticks. At parting he recommended her to Madam <hi>de Monteſpan</hi>'s eare, to whom he wrote oftner then his cuſtom uſual<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly was, that he might have the plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure &amp; diverſion to ſee the anſwers which <hi>Scaron</hi> dictated: He found 'em all ſo agreable and charming, the language ſo beautiful, the thoughts ſo natural and tender, that he redoubled his Viſits, and never failed when he was there, to enter into ſome pleaſant facetious converſation with her. All this, you may imagine, was not very grate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful to her Miſtreſs, who began now to be ſenſible, that after the example of Madam, ſhe had made a perſon known to the King, who was in a capacity to ſupplant her. <hi>Scaron,</hi> who likewiſe perceived the alteration which theſe unex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pected favours from his Majeſty, had created in <hi>Monteſpan,</hi> endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voured
<pb n="113" facs="tcp:58078:62"/>all ſhe could to poſſeſher with far different Sentiments, and attended her with greater dili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gence every day than other, which in ſome ſort ſerved to cure her diſguſt.</p>
            <p>The King took ſuch Pleaſure in her Converſation, that he ſeemed to be ſomewhat in Love. In effect, he perceived himſelf to be touched with a cortain Paſſion in her favour: He gave himſelf no great trouble to reſiſt and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bat theſe growing Inclinations, ſuppoſing that they would vaniſh of themſelves as ſoon as they were born, but herein he was mightily miſtaken: For his Affe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions increaſed ſo violently, that he reſolved to Diſcourſe her a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout them the very next opportu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity. To be ſhort, one day when <hi>Monteſpan</hi> was indiſpoſed with a Fever, and had compoſed her ſelf
<pb n="114" facs="tcp:58078:63"/>to reſt, the King entred <hi>Scaron's</hi> Apartment; as ſoon as ever he was entred, the reſt of the Maids withdrew out of a reſpect to the King, ſo that finding himſelf all alone with her, he thus accoſtell her. It it ſome days ago Madam, ſays he, ſince I have felt a certain <hi>Je ne ſay quoi</hi> for you, which obli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges me to regard you with a greater Tenderneſs, than meer Good-will uſes to inſpire People with. I have often ſought an occaſion to make this Declarati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on to you, and at the ſame time to requeſt you to bring me ſome Remedy for my Pain: but having never as yet found ſo favourable an opportunity as this at preſent, I conjure you to comply with my Demands, and to recoive the offer I tender you, of being the abſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lute Miſtreſs of my Heart and Kingdom. Alas! Sir, anſwered
<pb n="115" facs="tcp:58078:63"/>ſhe, how ready is your Majeſty to sally your popr undeſerving Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vants. How! was it enough to divert your ſelf upon the Score of my Writing, but you muſt find out at new Subject for your laughter? How ever, I ought to eſteem my ſelf ſufficiently happy, in that I am able to contribute a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny thing to the Pleaſure of the greateſt Monarch in the World, tho' it is all at my own Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pened</p>
            <p>No, no, Madam, replys he, ſomewhat haſtily, theſe are not proper Subjects for Raillery, what I have ſaid to you, is no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing out the truth, I am ſincere, believe me upon my word, and comply with my Paſſion. Is it poſſible then ſays ſhe, perſuing her Diſcourſe, that a mighty Prince ſhould caſt his Eyes ſo low? Sir, I am not worthy of ſuch an Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour,
<pb n="116" facs="tcp:58078:64"/>and beſides, the inumera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Company of Beauties, the moſt exquiſite in the World, of which your Court is ſo full, are ſiſter by far to engage the Heart of ſo great a Man. The World would be apt to conclude that your Majeſty is blind as to theſe. Matters, and as for my ſelf, they would give me a Name, which does not at all belong to me. In fine Sir, beſides that I am ſome what advanced in Age, &amp; want Charms enough to pretend to ſo glorious a Conqueſt, your Majeſty muſt not be ignorant that I am a Widow, and that you cannot poſſibly make choice of a Perſon that lyes un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der ſo many diſadvantages as my<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf, without making her draw down upon her Head the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempt and indignation of all the beautiful Sex. Ah! Madam, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plyes the King, 'Tis to no purpoſe
<pb n="117" facs="tcp:58078:64"/>to ſeek for ſuch little Subter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuges-as theſe to colour your re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſal. Are you reſolved to make me languiſh away a miſerable Life? Ought you nor rather to reſt ſatisfied, when Her you ſee, that altho' I am above the reſt of mankind, yet never theleſs I have a Heart which is ſuſceptable of all the pretty ſoft engaging things of Love? and ſuch I eſteem, that lively penetrating Wit, which one ſees in you, that Grandeur of Soul which you make appear in the moſt inconſiderable Acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons; in a word, all your charm<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Perfections.</p>
            <p>He ſaid no more to her at that time, and at parting made her a profound reverence, and bid her conſider of what had paſſed be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween them. She had no time to return any Anſwer, for the King immediate entred Madam
<pb n="118" facs="tcp:58078:65"/>
               <hi>de Manteſpan</hi>'s Apartment, where his <hi>Chagrin</hi> would not ſuffer him to carry long.</p>
            <p>As ſoon as he was gone, <hi>Made<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moiſell Scaron</hi> revolved all this Converſation in her mind; ſhe repreſented to her ſelf the Paſſion which the King expreſſed for her, and did not at all queſtion but that ſhe was beloved by him. Never theleſe, ſhe took up a reſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lution to diſſemble a little upon this Score, to the end that by a pretended reſiſtance ſhe might inflame the Kings Deſires. This piece of Policy ſucceeded beyond Expectation, for having ſuffered two of his Viſits, without ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king any Declaration in favour of him, ſhe threw him into ſo vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent a Paſſion, that being fully re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolved to vanquiſh her, he wrote the following the Letter.</p>
            <floatingText type="letter" xml:lang="eng">
               <body>
                  <pb n="119" facs="tcp:58078:65"/>
                  <head>The Letter of <hi>LOVIS</hi> XIV. To Madam <hi>Scaron,</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>I</hi> Am to tell you, Madam, that your reſiſtance has extremely aſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhed me; Mr, I ſay, that have been hitherto accuſtomed to Victory, and was never before refuſed. I aways believed that being a King, it was ſufficient to give any ſign of my deſire, in order to accompliſh it, but I perceive the contrary by your Rigeurs, and therefore to oblige you to ſoften them, was the occaſion of this Letter. Let me conjure you, my deareſt, to love me, or at leaſt make as if you loved me. To<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards Evening I ſhall come to ſee you, and if then I find you no more
<pb n="120" facs="tcp:58078:66"/>favourable to me, than at your other Viſits, you will reduce, to the extre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mity of Deſpair the moſt paſſionate of Lovers.</p>
                  <closer>
                     <signed>Lovis.</signed>
                  </closer>
               </body>
            </floatingText>
            <p>She received this Letter with an unſpeakable tranſport of joy, and finally determined to ſurren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der her ſelf, that very ſame Eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning to His Royal Pleaſure, for fear ſhe ſhould diſguſt or exaſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate him by a farther Affectation of reſiſtance. Madam <hi>de Mon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſpan,</hi> who perceived the In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trigue, was extremely afflicted, but being very well read in Court-Policies, ſhe diſſembled her Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſentment, and ſhewed no appea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rances of diſcontent. In the mean time, the King being come to her Chamber, ſhe endeavoured to retain him with her, by her Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſſes,
<pb n="121" facs="tcp:58078:66"/>but he had another deſign in his Head; he was deſirou to know, what mighty Effects his Letter had produced, ſo he quit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted her in haſte, and ran to the Apartment of his new Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtreſs. As ſoon as ever ſhe per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived him, ſhe put her ſelf into a poſture of weeping. The King was urgent with her, to know the occaſion. Alaſs! Sir, ſays ſhe, I bewail my weakneſs, which notwithſtanding is powerful e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough to triumph over my Duty, and my Honour: For in fine, it is impoſſible for me to reſiſt you any longer, you are my King, I owe every thing to you ... But —No, Madam, replyes he to her, I am not willing you ſhould do any thing by Force and Compul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion. I will lay aſide the Qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity of a Soveraign before you; do you lay aſide your Cruelty
<pb n="122" facs="tcp:58078:67"/>and Rigour, and with a recipro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cal Paſſion, Love thoſe that love you.</p>
            <p>He ſaid to her upon this occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, abundance of tender, agree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able things, by the force of which ſhe ſuffered her ſelf at laſt to be overcome, and thus the King in that favourable moment accom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pliſhed his Deſign, and after ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veral reiterated Careſſes, they took their leaves of one another for a few days. The King gave Orders to have a Magnificent A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>partment furniſhed for her, which he prayed her to accept; and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing willing, that ſhe ſhould not appear under a meaner Chara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cter than any of his former Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtreſſes, he lookt out a Title for her, and at laſt conferred upon her, that of the Marchioneſs <hi>de Maintenon.</hi> But that Dignity be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing only Honorary, he purchaſed
<pb n="123" facs="tcp:58078:67"/>the Eſtate of Marquis <hi>de Mainte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>non</hi> for her, who parted with it willingly, and received as well as ſhe a large ſhare of his Maje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſties Royal Gratifications; for he had a Frigat in <hi>America</hi> defrayed at the Kings Expence for the ſpace of four or five Years, to make what advantaget he could by her, and withal, a Permiſſion to execute what Acts of Piracy he pleaſed upon the <hi>Spaniards.</hi> If he had been Maſter of any Courage, and had known how to manage his Fortune, when the <hi>Fributiers</hi> de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſired him to joyn with them, he had been without diſpute the ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cheſt Man that <hi>France</hi> had in all her Dominions. But he was far from attempting any thing that was Heroic, he had always baſeneſs enough to ſteal out of the Fleet, when he ſaw there was any occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion for Fighting, but at the time
<pb n="124" facs="tcp:58078:68"/>of ſharing the ſpoil, he never failed to pay his Attendance, and by his Good-will would have re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived the greateſt part of the Dividend. This ſcandalous Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duct ſunk him very low in his Reputation, and at preſent he is ſo mortally hated by all theſe People, that a Party of them ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving taken him Priſoner in the Year 85, when he came from <hi>En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rope,</hi> to the Iſle of St. <hi>Martin,</hi> deſigned to put him and his Lady to the Sword, after they had plun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dered them: Nevertheleſs, Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſſion prevailed upon them at laſt, ſo they gave him his Life, and having taken his Ship from him, they left him only a little Shal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lop to get a ſhore, of which he was then in ſight. But if they ever meet him the Second time, it is likely to be his laſt; and in all Probability they'l never give
<pb n="125" facs="tcp:58078:68"/>him an opportunity of meeting them the Third time. To re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aſſume our Diſcourſe; the King having made this purchaſe, ſpa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red no Charges to make the place agreeable to his Miſtreſs: He laid a prodigious infinite Expence up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on it, he brought ſtore of Water thither, tho before he could bring his deſign to Execution, he was forced of neceſſity to raiſe Moun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tains, and Traverſe them. To this end he joyned Hills together, at the incredible Drudgery of his poor People; for it coſt the Lives of above Threeſcore thouſand Souls, and all this, to gratifie a brutal inſatiable Paſſion, with which He was ever poſſeſſed.</p>
            <p>Madam <hi>de Scaron,</hi> whom we ſhall for the future call by the Name of <hi>Maintenon,</hi> was not wanting to pay the King the Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledements for all his Favours.
<pb n="126" facs="tcp:58078:69"/>She conſtantly paſſed two hours in a day in private with him, he ſometimes Communicated to her Affairs of the greateſt Importance, and ſometimes he alſo followed her Advice.</p>
            <p>In the mean time, ſhe did not behave her ſelf diſrepectfully to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards Madam <hi>de Monteſpan,</hi> ſhe treated her always with a great deal of Eſteem and Moderation, &amp; this prudent Conduct ſerved to preſerve a good intelligence be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween them for a long time.</p>
            <p>The Reverend Fathers the Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuites, no ſooner perceived the Elevation of <hi>Maintenon,</hi> but they immediately reſolved to gain her to their Party; they rendred her all manner of Homage and Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion, of which fulſome Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vices the Society is liberal enough, when they find their Account in doing it. They ordered the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verend
<pb n="127" facs="tcp:58078:69"/>Father <hi>la Chaiſe</hi> and <hi>Bour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dalou</hi> to thank his Majeſty, and to inſinuate to him, that he could not have made a fitter Choice of any Perſon to entertain his va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cant Intervals, than what he had already made; they eſtabliſhed her ſo far in his good Opinion, that ſhe was extremely glad to ſee them at her Houſe. In fine, to teſtifie the Confidence which ſhe had in that Order, ſhe choſe from thence a Spiritual Director of her Conſcience; nay, ſhe en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tred her ſelf into the Third Order of the Society, and would by all means carry the Name of a Daughter of that ſanctified Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany. However, even this Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſcenſion did not fatisfie the Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuites, but being informed by her Confeſſor. (For theſe are a ſort of Eccleſiaſtical Pimps you muſt underſtand, that never Scruple to
<pb n="128" facs="tcp:58078:70"/>diſcover any Secret, when it makes for the intereſt of their Order) that ſhe was exceedingly given to the Pleaſures of the Fleſh, and that ſhe entertained an amorous Correſpondence with one of her Domeſticks, they una<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nimouſly deſired him in a full Aſſembly, which they held in the College <hi>de Montaign,</hi> that he would contribute as far as in him lay, to let them make an abſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lute Conqueſt of her, to the end that they might have her entirely at their Devotion. He promiſed to uſe his utmoſt Efforts for the Advancement of the holy Socie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, and to give him his due Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racter, he left nothing unattemp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted: To bring the buſineſs about more dextrouſly, he took care that his Confeſſor in ordinary ſhould pretend a certain indiſpoſition for a time, ſo ſhe was forced to make
<pb n="129" facs="tcp:58078:70"/>uſe of the Jeſuit, and for his part he cou'd not have wiſhed for a better opportunity; for by this means he diſcover'd the turnings and windings of her Conſcience; and was ſo far from chaſtizing her for her Sins, that he aſſured her ſhe was not at all accountable for 'em, but that ſhe was obliged by all the ties of Chriſtianity, to furniſh herſelf with Amorous inſtructions, in order to render her ſelf Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viceable to the pleaſures of the Eldeſt Son of the Church.</p>
            <p>Sinners uſually love to be flat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter'd in their Crimes, and to find out a way to damn themſelves with pleaſure; and this is the me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thod that the Modern Caſuiſts, the Jeſuites preſcribe to their Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitents, that make no other uſe of this Sacred Tribunal, which if rightly managed ought to be an inſtrument of ſaving People, but
<pb n="130" facs="tcp:58078:71"/>only to chalk out to 'em the moſt compendious Way to Hell. It is no wonder therefore, that <hi>Main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenon</hi> abandon'd her ſelf to ſuch bleſſed Counſellors, who had found out ſo rare an expedient; and ſhe had no ſooner taſted the ſoftneſs and bounties of Father <hi>la Chaiſe</hi> in her Confeſſion, but ſhe rejected the reſt of the Eccleſiaſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cal herd; in effect, after that time ſhe only made uſe of him. All this while, he had promiſed to make a conqueſt of her perſon by way of a Love Intrigue; To ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceed in this attempt, by the help of a little Spiritual Opium, he lull'd aſleep the Conſciences of all her Domeſticks, whom he found favourably inclined to the Society, and like a Politick director he employed ſome of his own crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures in this pious affair; and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt others, two penitential
<pb n="131" facs="tcp:58078:71"/>Siſters of the Society, who had an admirable faculty at wheedling and cajoling, and who had in a ſhort time ſo ſtrangely eſtabliſh'd themſelves in <hi>Maintenon</hi>'s good opinion, that ſhe repoſed an en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tire confidence in 'em, and by way of requital made uſe of 'em to ſerve her in her amorous affairs. By this means Father <hi>la Chaiſe</hi> was folly inform'd of every particular, and knew how to take his mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſures accordingly. One day, the Domeſtick, who was ſo very ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viceable to her in her nocturnal diverſions, had leave of her to go into the the Country for two days, but whether it was, that he met with any of his acquaintance there, or was willing to recruit himſelf with freſh vigour againſt his re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turn; he tarried ſomewhat lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger than he had permiſſion. After he had been abſent for the ſpace
<pb n="132" facs="tcp:58078:72"/>of ſix tedious days, Madam <hi>de Maintenon,</hi> who was never ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſtom'd to ſo long a faſt, wrote a Billet to him, and gave it one of her truſty confidents to ſee it deliver'd. The Maid immediately carried it to the Reverend Father <hi>le Chaiſe;</hi> they ſhut themſelves up in their Chamber, and having opened it, read as follows.</p>
            <floatingText type="letter" xml:lang="eng">
               <body>
                  <p>UPon my Word, my dear, I muſt reproach you for the ſmall tenderneſs you have for me; if you meaſur'd your own impatience by that of mine, you had return'd the very firſt day. As for my ſelf I can aſſure you, that I am infinitely diſpleaſed with my eaſineſs in gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving you leave to go, and I am yet the more concerned that you come not at all: You muſt either not love me, or be dead to, make ſo unpar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>donable a ſtay. Return then, my
<pb n="133" facs="tcp:58078:72"/>dear, and leave me not to ſuffer a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny more from the King's Embraces, whom I don't love the tenth part ſo well as thee; and if you wou'd not find me ſick, or dead, come at the uſual hour ſtraight into my Cham<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber; I ſhall give orders that my door be left open to let thee in. Adieu my Dear.</p>
               </body>
            </floatingText>
            <p>Goodly, Goodly! ſays the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, and what think you now? What I, ſays ſhe? I can't tell, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs it be that you'l give me the Letter to deliver it to him. No, by no means child, ſays he, but I want your aſſiſtance to do me a certain kindneſs: She made no great difficulty to promiſe it. 'Tis this, continues he, I'le go imme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diately and write a ſham-Letter to the Gallant, to ſpoil his coming and at the bleſſed hour of Aſſig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation I'le not fail to expect you
<pb n="134" facs="tcp:58078:73"/>in the Anti-chamber, from whence you muſt lead me to her Bed, the place of Execution. I am much of the ſame pitch and ſtature with him, and will throw upon my ſelf all the conſequences of this affair.</p>
            <p>The buſineſs being thus reſol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved upon, he made all the haſte he could to write the Bantering Letter, and gave it her to ſee it deliver'd inſtead of the other. It was conceived in theſe terms.</p>
            <floatingText type="letter" xml:lang="eng">
               <body>
                  <opener>
                     <salute>Sir,</salute>
                  </opener>
                  <p>
                     <hi>I</hi> Am ſenſibly afflicted that I muſt acquaint you with ill News. Your Father is at the point of death, I have confeſs'd him this Morning, and given him the Holy Viaticum. He deſired me two or three times to write to you, becauſe he has ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing of moment to communicate to you before he dies: Fail not there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore to take Horſe immediately upon
<pb n="135" facs="tcp:58078:73"/>the receipt of this, for as yet he is in his ſenſes; and if you loſe no time, according to what we are able to judge by all ontward appea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rances, you may come ſoon enough to ſpeak with him.</p>
                  <closer>
                     <signed>Cochonet, Curate de Laſine.</signed>
                  </closer>
               </body>
            </floatingText>
            <p>He had no ſooner received this Letter, but he effectually be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieved, that the Matter was ſo. He had an extraordinary Ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derneſs for his Father, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore made all the diſpatch he could, to ſee him; but to his great ſurprize he found him in very good Health, which did not a little rejoyce him. They were not able to underſtand the Myſtery of this Letter, but our young Gallant had not the leaſt Jealou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſie
<pb n="136" facs="tcp:58078:74"/>of the real occaſion, which made him to continue for ſome time with his Parents. In the mean time, the Reverend Father <hi>la Chaiſe</hi> came exactly at the hour appointed to the Anti-Chamber, when he found the Maid expect<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing him. He undreſſed himſelf, and put on a Night-gown and Cap, which was the Equipage the other Gentleman uſed in his amorous Expeditions; after this he was introduced to her Bed, where he entred ſoftly, and with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out any farther Ceremony pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pared for the Aſſault. Altho' ſhe was faſt aſleep, ſhe perceived him well enough, notwithſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding the Pretenſions of ſome cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain Females who are of another Opinion, and ſuppoſing it to be her own Game-Bull in ordinary, ſhe embraced him with ſuch vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent
<pb n="137" facs="tcp:58078:74"/>and eager Careſſes, that the poor Father thought he ſhould expire in this charming Exerciſe. The Sport was too entertaining to leave any Room for dull inſipid Converſation; thus they renew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed the Combat ſeveral times without uttering one Syllable, and in all Probability they had paſſed the Night after this man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner, if Father <hi>la Chaiſe</hi> had not broke the ſilence by reaſon of a dam'd unlucky Cold, which ſet him a Coughing and Wheezing like a decrepit Alderman, that e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>every Morning Vomits ropes of Phlegm by whole-Sale, as juglers do inkle at a Country Fair. Madam <hi>de Maintenon</hi> gave a ſhriek im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mediately, and would have thrown her ſelf out of Bed; but our Eccleſiaſtical Stallion held her faſt, and all the while made her
<pb n="138" facs="tcp:58078:75"/>the moſt plauſible Excuſes, that either his Fear or his Love could ſuggeſt to him: After he had ſomewhat appeaſed the Storm, and calmed her, he repreſented to her, that the thing was with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out Remedy; that ſhe ought to conſider it was the violence of his Paſſion, which obliged him to do it, but ſtill he was ſo prudent, as not to make the leaſt diſcovery of the true Motive of this Intrigue. How they came to be reconciled, I am not able to ſay; but in fine, my Memoirs tell me, that recon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciled they were, and the buſineſs fairly accommodated between them. When the Tempeſt was happily blown over, they paſſed the remainder of the Night in theſe laudable Recreations, and if we may give any Credit to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terior appearances, they have pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſued
<pb n="139" facs="tcp:58078:75"/>the ſame Sport ever ſince; and I have the Charity to believe they'l continue the Game as long as either of them are able. For certain it is; that if She's the King's Mule; She's likewiſe the Mare of the pious <hi>la Chaiſe,</hi> and her <hi>Valet</hi>'s Hackney into the Bar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain, who poor Fellow was no ſooner returned to his Miſtreſs, but he excuſed his long abſence, upon the Account of the Sham-Letter he had received. But ſhe who was advertiſed of the whole Affair, by Father <hi>la Chaiſe,</hi> was not deſirous to ſearch any farther in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to theſe Matters, and received him into her Favour; ſince which time ſhe employs him in her Pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitive Drudgery to her vaſt Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfaction, if we may take a cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain Talkative, buſie Gentlewo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mans word for it, whom the vul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gar
<pb n="140" facs="tcp:58078:76"/>People call Fame. All theſe liberal Contributions by the bye, did not hinder her from recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving the Kings ordinary Benevo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence, when he was in Health, and in a Capacity of performing; but when his Diſtemper came upon him, which proceeded from no other cauſe than his over-exhau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſting his Royal Loyns, Madam <hi>de Maintenon</hi> was infinitely affli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted, and in publick gave all the Demonſtrations of Grief imagina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble. In fine, the Malady grow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing daily worſe and worſe, the Phyſicians reſolved to apply Plai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters to the part affected: This holy Daughter of the Society, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing very well ſatisfied in her Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience, that ſhe was partly the occaſion of his Majeſties indiſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſition, generouſly offered to lay the firſt Plaiſter on this diſtreſſed
<pb n="141" facs="tcp:58078:76"/>Son of <hi>Priapus.</hi> She laid it on accordingly, and continued to do it ſeveral times, even until the entire recovery of the King: When ſhe ſaw him reſtored to his Health, ſhe was willing to divert him, and having nothing at all of that nice delicate Love in her which won't admit of a Compe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titor, ſhe found out for him one of the moſt celebrated Beauties in <hi>France.</hi> 'Twas Madam <hi>Fon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tange,</hi> which ſhe preſented to him; the King redoubled his Eſteem for her, ſeeing ſhe made as it were a Sacrifice of her ſelf, and likewiſe cheriſhed <hi>Fontange</hi> with a very particular Affection; But their Amours having been already written, we think it not worth the while, to make any impertinent Repetitions of them in this place; only this I will
<pb n="142" facs="tcp:58078:77"/>add, that the King did not en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joy her long, for ſhe was Poiſon'd. Madam <hi>de Maintenon</hi> has entire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly poſſeſſed the King's inclinati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons ever ſince; and whatever Charms he might find to attract him elſewhere; yet they were never ſo powerful as hers ſince the Death of <hi>Fontange.</hi> He like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe received another Preſent from her hands, and that was <hi>la' Martenon;</hi> but ſhe died in Child-Bed, ſo that when ſhe came to offer him another Lady for his Royal diverſion, he would not accept the Gift, but applied him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf altogether to her; who for her part is not overmuch affli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted, altho' the King has not been for a conſiderable time, capable to oblige any of the fair Sex; but has ſo much Diſcretion, as to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve her Neceſſities elſewhere,
<pb n="143" facs="tcp:58078:77"/>His Majeſties favour is more acceptable and grateful to her then his Love, ſince ſhe has ſo many ſervile Vaſſals, to gratifie her infamous Paſſions, and above the reſt, the Reverend Father <hi>la Chaiſe.</hi>
            </p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
